Good morning. Good morning. And thanks for coming. Alma loves it. I love it. Charlie
loves it. We're glad to have you here. We're going to make this preliminary before the
question is very short because we want to get in at least 60 questions half divided
by the audience outside this arena and half from you.
So, I would just like to get right to the directors and the earnings that have been put up on the
web page this morning.
But we'll cover those very fast and we'll get to the questions now.
I, when I woke up this morning, I realized that we had a competitive broadcast going
out somewhere in the UK.
And they were celebrating King Charles.
And we've got our own King Charles here today.
[APPLAUSE]
And next to him, we have Greg Abel, who's
in charge of all the operations except for insurance.
Next.
[APPLAUSE]
And next to Greg, we have a man I ran into in 1986,
and has made us look good ever since.
We have a man in charge of insurance, Ajit Jain.
[APPLAUSE]
And now we have our directors here in front,
and if they would just stand briefly,
and then I'll go on to the next one,
and they're all here today, first of all,
doing alphabetically.
There's Howard Buffett.
(audience applauding)
There's Suzy Buffett.
Mr. Steve Burke, Ken Schnault, Chris Davis, Sue Decker, Charlotte Geiman, Tom Murphy
Jr., Ron Olson, Wally Weiss, and Merrill Whitmer. That's as good as you can get. And there's
one other person I would like to mention before we get on to the earnings that were put on
in the press release this morning.
Well, let's see who we have here.
We've got, this is hard to believe.
Can you imagine a name?
Melissa Shapiro Shapiro.
She was, Melissa Shapiro just married another Shapiro,
And she put this whole thing together with no help from me, no help from Charlie,
and a lot of help from the people in the other room.
Melissa.
Yeah, it's very easy if you can remember her second name, you can remember her third name.
So, "Mum, this is Shapiro, Shapiro." And with that, I would like to
Next move on to the earnings in a couple small slides that explain what we're all about and
then we're going to get to the Q&A. And the slide is up behind me. Yeah, there it is. We reported
in the first quarter operating earnings a little over eight billion. And when we talk about operating
earnings. We're basically referring to the earnings of Berkshire half a way as generally,
well, as required under GAP, excluding, however, capital gains both realized and unrealized.
There's a few other very minor items, but basically we expect to make capital gains
over time. Why would we own the stocks otherwise? It doesn't always work out, but overall it
works out pretty well over time. But in any day, any quarter, any year, even occasionally
over a five-year period, the stock prices move around capriciously. Now we own a lot
of other businesses. We consider those stocks businesses. We own a lot of other businesses
where they get consolidated, and they don't move around in value. Now if we had a little
bit of Burlington stock outstanding, if we had a little bit of the energy stock trading,
those stocks would move around a lot. But the businesses are what count. So the operating
earnings, as you'll see in the first quarter, came in at about $8 billion. And I would say
that in the general economy, the feedback we get is that I would say perhaps the majority
of our businesses will actually report lower earnings this year than last year.
In various degrees in the last six months or so, at various times, the businesses have
have left the incredible period, which is about as extraordinary as I've seen in business
since World War II, with the government that would port out a lot of money to people who
couldn't get goods, it was more extreme in World War II.
But this was extreme this time.
And it was just a question of getting goods to the liver and people bought, and they didn't
wait for sales.
If you couldn't sell them one thing, they would put another thing in the backlog.
It was an extraordinary period.
And that period has ended.
It hasn't ended with, you know, it isn't that employment's fell off or off a cliff or anything
in the least, but it is a different climate than it was six months ago.
And a number of our managers were surprised.
I'm not mad too much inventory on order,
and then all of a sudden it got delivered,
and people weren't in the same frame of mind as earlier.
And now we'll start having sales
at places where we didn't need to have sales before.
But despite the fact that this year,
I think in general will be slower,
than last year, we actually are situated
so that I would expect, and believe me,
When I say accept, expect, it's nothing is sure.
Nothing's sure tomorrow, nothing's sure next year,
and nothing is ever sure, either in markets
or in business forecasts or anything else.
And we don't pay much attention to markets or forecasts
unless the markets happen to offer
something interesting to do.
But nevertheless, we are positioned in two respects
you'll see from this first report. Our investment income is going to be a lot
larger this year than last year and that's built in. I mean we had, as you'll
see in a minute, we've had $125 billion or so in very short-term investments and
And believe it or not, not that long ago, we were getting four basis points, which is
next to nothing, on that $125 billion, which means we were getting $50 million a year.
And now the same money, the other just day or day before yesterday, we actually bought
because of some funny twist in the market because of doubts about the deficit ceiling,
the debt ceiling. We bought 3 billion of bills at a 5.90. That's 5.9. It was a 5.92. Bond
equivalent yield. So we will have what produced us not that long ago on a 12-month basis was
producing 50 million a year, producing something in the area of 5 billion a year. So we're
in a position where the investment income is essentially, well it is certain to increase
quite a bit.
And insurance underwriting is not, it does not correlate with business activity.
It depends on things like hurricanes and earthquakes and other events.
So on a prospective basis, on a probability basis, we're likely to have a better year
this year in insurance underwriting than we had last year.
It just isn't affected by what you might call the business cycle or what applies to generally
an industry, detailing, you name it.
So I would expect, and one massive earthquake or one hurricane that came into just the wrong
place would can affect that prediction, but on a probabilistic basis, our insurance looks
better this year.
So if you get two of those, two of the elements there of our main elements of earnings that
look like they will swing in our direction, I would expect, but I can't promise, I would
that are operating in earnings will be greater than last year.
And if we'll move to the second slide,
I give you those operating earnings figures
just to give you a overview of what has happened
since the pandemic started and often the year before as a base.
And we retain all our earnings, as you know.
So if we're retaining 30 or 35 billion
or whatever it may be a year,
you should expect more operating earnings over time.
I mean, this number should be significantly higher,
five or 10 or 15 years from now,
because we have the advantage of retaining earnings.
And that's what got us to these figures,
because they were essentially nothing when we started.
And they got there by retaining earnings
and we'll keep retaining earnings.
So it's no great triumph if these numbers move up.
And what we hope is that they move up
at a reasonable rate.
Historically, they moved up at an unreasonable rate
sometimes, but we were working with much smaller sums then.
And that can't be repeated with our present capital base.
Because I note there--
I believe it's on this slide.
Let's take a look.
Now that'll be, let's see, it's on the,
well on the next, on the next place paid,
let's move to the next slide.
We show that we had on March 31st,
now 500, was it 504 billion of gap net worth.
Now what might surprise you is that there's
No other company in the United States, no other company that has a number that is that
large.
Now, that isn't because we've got the most valuable company in the United States.
Other companies have used their money to repurchase shares.
They could have accumulated 504 billion in gap.
Basically, we have more undergap accounting now than any other company in the U.S.
And of course, if you measure return on equity, that becomes a very big number to increase
at a rapid rate, but we hope to do so.
Not a rapid rate, a decent rate.
And right below that you see something called float.
And float is money that is left in our hands somewhat akin, but very importantly different
than a bank deposit.
But you have to pay interest to get a bank deposit.
You have to pay more interest these days, and you have to run a bank and do a lot of
things.
And basically, this is money that represents unpaid losses at this time.
You get paid in advance in insurance.
So what shows up as a net liability on our balance sheet is, gives us funds to exercise
with an amount of discretion that no other insurance company that I know of in the world
and joy just because we have so much net worth.
And our float now comes to $165 billion, and the man sitting on the far left is responsible
for moving that number up from a piton in 1986 to this incredible figure, which in most
years, practically all years, hasn't cost us anything.
So it's like having a bank with no employees, no interest, and no ability to withdraw the
money in a hurry that we have working for us.
And it's a very valuable asset that shows up as a liability.
And Ajit is responsible for building up this treasure, which has been done by out-competing
insurance companies all over the world.
And now a number of our insurance companies, in turn, are run by talented managers who
who contributed one way or another.
Start with Geico, the beginning of my career,
and that float.
If you think about it, just think of a balance sheet.
You've got liabilities here, and you've got assets over here,
and the liability side finances the asset side.
It's very simple.
And stockholders' equity finances it,
long-term debt finances it, and so on.
But stockholders' equity is very expensive in a real sense.
Long term debt has been cheap for a while, but it can get expensive and it can also become
due eventually and it may not be available.
But float is another item that shows, it's a liability, but it hasn't cost us anything
And it can't disappear in a hurry.
And it finances the asset side in the same way
as stockholders' equity.
And nobody else thinks of it much that way,
but we've always thought of it that way,
and it's built up over time.
So I show at the bottom what's happened with cash
and treasury bills through March 31st.
And I will tell you that in the month of April,
We probably added about $7 billion to that factor.
Not part of that is because we didn't buy as much stock because that reduces cash and
treasury bills.
We bought about $400 million worth of stock in the month of April.
That's a minus in terms of cash available.
And we, however, sold net some stock which produced maybe $4 billion.
And of course we had operating earnings, probably $2.5 billion or something in that area.
My guess is we probably increased our cash in Treasuryables, $6 billion or $7 billion
in the month.
And I just want to give you a feel for how the cash flows at Berkshire.
And then if we move to the final,
I think it's the final one, next to the last one.
No, I think it is the last one, let's see, is the fourth.
Yeah, is this, we should have the one up there,
class A equivalent shares outstanding.
And you'll notice that every year,
the number of our shares go down.
So if we own more businesses,
and the businesses make more money,
Your share, as shareholders, as owners of Berkshire,
increases every year without you laying out any money.
Now you're laying out the alternative
which you could receive in dividends,
but the reason we got into where we are
is because we kept the money.
We did pay a dividend in 1967, 10 cents a share.
It was a terrible mistake.
And I always tell people that I'd left for the men's room
and the directors voted while I was going.
But that isn't true.
I was there.
I confess.
But we very invested and that's produced the 500 billion
plus of shareholders' equity and the 30 billion plus
of operating earnings.
And we'll continue to follow that policy
because it makes a great deal of sense.
And with that, I think we've taken care of the preliminaries.
You can study that the 10Q is on the web page.
And if you have a week or two vacation,
you could spend it reading the 10Q.
But that is the essence of Berkshire.
And with that, I will start with Becky Quick.
And we will alternate between Becky and the audience,
and her questions have come in from all over the country.
And I believe you identified the center.
And go to it, Becky.
Thanks, Warren.
The first question comes in from Randy Jeffs in Irvine,
California.
And his question is, if Silicon Valley Bank's deposit had not
been fully covered, what do you think the economic consequences
would have been to the nation?
Well, I would just simply say it would have been catastrophic.
And that's why they were covered.
And even though the FDIC limit is $250,000,
that's the way the statute reads.
But that is not the way the US is going to behave any more
than they're going to let the Dutch ceiling cause the world
to go into turmoil.
And they, well they just, I can't imagine anybody in the administration, in the Congress,
in the Federal Reserve, whatever it may have been, FDIC.
I can't imagine anybody saying, I'd like to be the one on television tomorrow and explain
the American public while we're keeping only $250,000 insured, and we're going to start
around every bank in the country and disrupt the world financial system.
So I think it was inevitable.
Charlie, do you have any?
No, I have nothing to add.
Okay, well, incidentally, I should mention this now.
Ajit and Greg will be here in the morning session, which ends at noon.
And so it's got questions to direct to them.
The time to do it is in the first half of the show.
And then after lunch, it'll just, Charlie and I will be back.
OK. Area one.
Hi, Nerov Patel, Harrell, Massachusetts.
Mr. Buffett, Mr. Munger, it seems like you found the sweet spot between being too conservative
and too aggressive as investors.
Do you ever make bad investment decisions because of your emotions, and what do you
do to try to keep that from happening?
Well, we make bad investment decisions.
plenty of times I make more than Charlie because I like to think it's because I make more decisions,
but probably more batting average is worse. But I can't recall any time in the history of Berkshire
we made an emotional decision. I know the movie had Jamie Lee in there, but that was for laughs.
I mean, Jamie Lee, she's good, but she's not good enough to get me or Charlie to make
an emotional decision.
Charlie, I'm sure you have something to add on that.
Well, it's a different movie that is shown at most corporate meetings.
Yeah.
But have we ever made an emotional decision?
No.
That's in business we're talking about.
Yeah.
No, you don't want to be a no emotion person in all of your life, but you definitely want
be no emotion person in making an investment or business decision.
You can argue that.
We probably, I would say that we've made an emotional decision perhaps, and when a manager
has been with us for some period.
And we have ignored the fact that perhaps they weren't quite what they were earlier.
But our businesses are so good that they've run better sometimes.
When I've talked about Westco, for example, the wonderful Louisville incentive, it ran
on automatic pilot for a while.
I don't think we suffered by it, but you can argue that if Charlie and I hadn't liked
Louis as much as we did, we might have spotted it a little bit earlier, but I don't think
it made any difference in the results.
Would you agree with that, Charlie?
Yeah, yeah, you'd be totally with it.
And I'm glad we behaved the way we did at Westco.
By the way, we bought the thing for a few tens of millions and it became worth two or three
billion.
Yeah, that wasn't common in the savings and loan businesses, you may have noticed.
They really went crazy in that industry and we had a wonderful guy in Louis.
We didn't go crazy.
Yeah, we didn't go crazy.
Okay.
Becky?
Okay, Maggie?
This question comes from Ben Nol in Minneapolis.
He says he's a Berkshire shareholder of three decades, and he's attended many Berkshire
meetings.
He's here again this year.
And this is addressed to Ajit and Greg.
He says, "Last year I asked you about how GEICO and BNSF appeared to lose ground to
their leading competitors.
GEICO on Telematics and BNSF on precision-scheduled railroading.
Ajit, you responded by saying how you expected GEICO to make progress in a year or two.
you spoke about your pride in BNSF, but you didn't directly address the threat of precision
scheduled railroading. Will each of you please provide perspective on these competitive challenges
and our company's strategies to address them?
In terms of GEICO and telematics, let me make the observation that GEICO has certainly taken
the bull by the horns and has made rapid strides in terms of trying to bridge the gap in terms
of telematics and its competitors.
They have now reached a point where on all new business, close to 90 percent has a telematics
input to the pricing decision.
Unfortunately less than half of that is being taken up by the policy holders.
The other point I want to make is even though we have made improvements in terms of bridging
the gap on telematics, we still haven't started to realize the true benefit and the real culprit
of the bottleneck is technology.
Geico's technology needs a lot more work than I thought it did.
It has more than 500, actually more than 600 legacy systems that don't really talk to each
other and we are trying to compress them to no more than 15, 16 systems that all talk to
each other.
That's a monumental challenge and because of that, even though we have made improvements
in telematics, we still have a long way to go because of technology.
Because of that and because of the whole issue more broadly in terms of matching rate to
risk, GEICO is still work in progress.
I don't know if any of you had a chance to look at the first quarter results, but Gaiko
has had a very good first quarter coming in at a combined ratio of 93 and change, which
means a margin of six and change.
Even though that's very good, it's not something we can take to the bank because there are
two unusual items that contributed to it.
Firstly, we've had what is called prior year reserve releases.
We've reduced reserves for the previous years and that contributed to it.
And secondly, every year the first quarter tends to be a seasonally good quarter for
auto insurance writers.
So if you adjust those two factors, my guess is the end of the year, Greiko will end up
with a combined ratio just south of 100 as opposed to the target they're shooting for
is 96.
I hope they reach the target of 96 by the end of next year.
But instead of getting too excited about it, I think it's important to realize that even
if we reach 96, it will come at the expense of having lost policy holders.
There is a trade-off between profitability and growth.
And clearly we are going to emphasize profitability and not growth, and that will come at the
expense of policy holders.
So it will not be until two years from now that we'll be back on track fighting the battles
on both the profitability and the growth front.
>> Great.
>> Yeah.
>> Moving to BNSF, I'll start again
by expressing great pride in the BNSF team.
We have an exceptional group of led by Katie and her managers
that show up every day to do great work on the railroad.
At the same time, they would be the first to acknowledge there's more
to be done there.
the specific reference to precision, scheduled railroading,
the other large railroad, class A, other railroads
in the U.S. follow that, and including the two in Canada.
We're well aware of what they're doing,
and obviously pay close attention
to their operating metrics.
And our team strives every day to be more efficient, obviously.
I would say we balance it with the needs of our customers.
If I look back to pre-2022, so we look at the three-year period of 2019, 2020, 2021,
the BNSF team made significant progress on their efficiencies and delivering overall value back to
the shareholders and to their customers, and at the same time maintaining a very safe railroad
for our employees. So we're making excellent progress. That didn't stop last year. They made
great progress again the reality in 2022 as we did go through a period of time where we had to
call it reset the railroad. We came out of the pandemic there were the supply challenges. We
had certain other labor issues and other things going on at the port and the reality is our team
prioritized getting the railroad back in place for the long term. Not a short-term focus on hitting
certain operating metrics in 2022. We're well aware of where we were relative to those metrics,
but the real focus was to get the railroad reset in a safe manner such that we could deliver long
term value and long term service to our customers. And that's really what we'll continue to see with
that team. There'll be continual progress. There'll be years where it's not as quickly or even we go
backwards, but over the long term we'll be very, we'll see exceptional results from that
team and couldn't be more proud that we have that asset.
Thank you.
I would just, well he deserves, but both of them deserve applause.
I would like to add one thing.
He, at GEICO, Todd Combs was a jeep's choice, my choice, to go back to GEICO to work on
the problem of matching rate to risk, which is what insurance is all about.
And he arrived with exquisite timing right before the pandemic broke out and all kinds
of things changed.
But Todd is doing a wonderful job at Geico and he works closely with the Jeep because
he still has a home in Omaha.
He comes back here and we get together on the weekend sometimes too.
So that's been a remarkable accomplishment under difficult circumstances.
He's not all the way home, but he's made a very, very big change in multiple ways at
GEICO.
And then one other thing I would like to mention, there have been a lot of public companies
created in the last decade thereabouts in insurance.
And there's none of them that we would like to own.
And they always started out in their perspective saying this is a tech company, not an insurance
company.
Of course, they're in a tech company.
Everybody's, whether they're in insurance or a lot of other places, are using the facility,
but you still have to properly match rate to risk.
They invariably have reported the huge losses, they've eaten up capital, but there's been
one company that nobody has generally heard of.
There's only been one that I know of, a company started in the last 10 years that has been
an overwhelming success, and that's a company that Ajit and four people who joined with
them set to develop a new business. It's called Berkshire Hathaway Specialty. It now has,
what's the float? A Jeep?
>> Coming up to 12 billion.
>> Yeah. We've built more float than probably all these companies combined. We've now, it's
cost us essentially nothing in terms of an underwriting loss. The four people have turned
I don't know, 1500 around the world.
We took on the whole industry and we brought some unique talent
and the four people that came and now have,
like I said, 1500 or so worldwide.
And we brought capital and we brought capabilities
that really only Berkshire could supply.
So it was the combination of brains and talent and energy and money.
And no one has really successfully entered this space.
Plenty of people in this space who didn't like us coming.
And we did it without it.
It cost us a dime of entry.
And it's been unmatched by any of the companies that went public.
And people have seen us do it, but they can't duplicate it.
And that's what Ajit has created.
And Peter East would have led this group, Berkshire Hathaway especially.
And it's just remarkable.
So anyway, with that, let's go on.
Give him a hand for that.
Okay, let's go to section two.
Hi, Charlie. I'm Eloran. I'm Karen here from Singapore.
I'm glad you got that in.
Your priorities are right.
>> Yes, I have a question on AI and robotics. Here's my question. As AI and robotics continue
to advance, what do you believe will be the positive and negative impact of this technology
on both the stocks market and society as a whole? And are there any specific industries
and companies that you believe will be most impacted.
>> Karen, I thank you for asking Charlie that question.
[ Laughter ]
>> Hello.
If you went into BYD's factories in China,
You would see robotics going in at an unbelievable rate.
So we're going to see a lot more robotics in the world.
I am personally skeptical of some of the hype
that is going into artificial intelligence.
I think old-fashioned intelligence works pretty well.
[APPLAUSE]
There won't be anything in AI that replaces the gene.
State that unqualifiedly.
They can do amazing things.
Bill Gates brought me out of the latest,
maybe not the latest version,
but one he thought maybe I could handle,
which has to be careful with me
in terms of leading me too fast.
And it did these remarkable things.
It didn't, but it couldn't tell jokes.
Bill told me that ahead of time and it prepared me.
And it just isn't there.
But, you know, things like checking all the legal opinions, you know, since the beginning
of time and everything and eliminating all the...
I mean, it can do all kinds of things.
And when something can do all kinds of things, I get a little bit worried.
And because I know we won't be able to uninvent it.
And you know, we did invent for very, very good reason the atom bomb in World War II.
And it was enormously important that we did so.
But is it good for the next 200 years of the world that the ability to do so has been unleashed?
We didn't have any choice.
But when you start something, well, Einstein said after the atom bomb, he said, "This has
changed everything in the world except how men think."
And I would say the same thing may, not the same thing.
I don't mean that, but I mean, with AI,
it can change everything in the world, except
how men think and behave.
And that's a big step to take.
It's a good question, and it's the best answer we can give.
Becky?
- This question comes from Tom Seymour.
He says, "The first sentence of a recent
Financial Times article read, "Charlie Munger has warned of a brewing storm in the U.S.
commercial property market with American banks full of what he said were bad loans as property
prices fall.
Please elaborate on what's going on in commercial real estate.
How bad will the losses be and what sectors or geographies look particularly bad?
I'll just add an addendum from another viewer who wrote in and wanted to know if Berkshire
would be more active in commercial real estate as a result?
Well, Berkshire has never been very active in commercial real estate.
It works better for taxable investors than it does for corporations taxed away Berkshire
is.
So I don't anticipate huge effects on Berkshire, but I do think that the hollowing out of the
of the downtowns in the United States and elsewhere in the world is going to be quite
significant and quite unpleasant.
I think the country will get through it all right, but as they say, it will often involve
a different set of owners.
Yeah, and the buildings don't go away, but-
The owners do.
But most people like to buy with non-recourse in real estate.
And one time I asked Charlie, there was some real estate guy we were talking to him,
and how do they decide how much they can-- a building like this is worth?
And the answer is, it's whatever they can borrow without signing their name.
And if you look at real estate generally, you'll understand what the phenomenon is happening.
if you remind yourself that that's the attitude of most people that have become big in the
real estate business. And it does mean that the lenders are the ones that get the property.
And of course they don't want the property usually. So the real estate operator counts
on negotiating with them and the banks tend to extend and pretend.
There's all kinds of activities that arrive out of commercial real estate development,
which occurs on a big scale.
But it all has consequences.
And I think we're about, well, we are starting to see the consequences of people who could
borrow it two and a half percent and find out it doesn't work at current rates and they
handed it back to somebody that gave them all the money they needed to build it.
Charlie's had more experience than really.
Charlie got it started in real estate though.
I mean Charlie, Charlie.
Yeah, so it's difficult.
I like what we do better.
Well, as Charlie once said to me when I was leaving his house a few months ago, I was
busy and we talked for a couple of hours and I said to Charlie as I left, I just, I wasn't
anybody else in the house.
I said, except one daughter.
And I said, Charlie, I'll just keep doing what we've been doing.
And Charlie said, without looking up or pausing a second, he said, that's all you know how
to do, Warren.
[LAUGHTER]
He was right, too.
Station three, is it?
Hi.
My name is Zialo Z. I'm from Santa Clara, California.
And my question is to Charlie and Warren.
Given the rise of disruptive technologies that
can improve productivity significantly and AI being
one of them, how do you envision
the future of value investing in this new era and what adaptations or new
principles do you think investors should adopt and any recommendations for
investors to remain successful in this rapid changing landscape. Thank you.
Well I'm glad to take that one. I think value investors are going to have a
harder time now that there's so many of them competing for a diminished bunch of
opportunities. So my advice to value investors is to get used to making less.
And Charlie was been telling me the same thing the whole time we've known each other.
We get along wonderfully because...
We are making less.
Oh well, but that's mostly I think it's because of the larger...
We did better when we were younger.
We never thought we could manage $508 billion.
No, you never thought that.
But I would argue that there's going
to be plenty of opportunities.
And part of the reason they're requiring
you to be plenty of opportunities,
the tech doesn't make any difference or any of that.
I mean, if you look at how the world changed in the years,
since 1942, when I started, you'd say, well,
how does a kid that doesn't know anything
about airplanes, it doesn't know anything about engines and cars, it doesn't know anything
about electricity and all that.
But that's easy, isn't it?
That's not the...
The world's changing, doesn't it?
Or new things coming along don't take away the opportunities.
What gives you opportunities is other people doing dumb things.
And it's that...
And I would say that, well, the 58 years we've been running Berkshire, I would say there's
been a great increase in the number of people doing dumb things, and they do big dumb things.
And the reason they do it to some extent is because they can get money from other people
so much easier than when we started.
So you could start 10 or 15 dumb insurance companies in the last 10 years and you could
become rich if you were adroit at it, whether the business exceeded or not and the underwriters
got paid and the lawyers got paid.
And that creates, if that's done on a large scale, which it couldn't be done 58 years
ago, you couldn't get the money to do some of the dumb things that we wanted to do,
fortunately.
And so I think that investing has disappeared so much from this huge capitalistic market
that anybody can play in, but that the big money is in selling other people ideas that
that isn't outperforming, in outperforming.
And I think that, I think if you don't run too much money,
which we do, but if you're running small amounts of money,
I think the opportunities will be greater,
but then Charlie and I will always differ
on this subject.
He likes to tell me how gloomy the world is,
and I like to tell him we'll find something.
And so far we've both been kind of right.
Charlie, wouldn't you?
We're budging it, Sean, that or not.
There is so much money now in the hands of so many smart people,
all trying to outsmart one another
and out-promote one another, getting more money out of other people.
And it's a radically different world from the world we started in.
And I suppose it will have its opportunities,
but it's also going to have some unpleasant episodes.
>> But they're trying to outsmart each other in arenas.
You don't have to play.
I mean, if you look at that government bond market,
the Treasury Bill market, I mean, you've got this one bill
that's out of line with the others.
We bought over $3 billion of it the other day.
And but those are people the world is overwhelmingly short term focused and if you go to an investor
relations call they're all trying to figure out how to fill out a sheet to show the earnings
for the year and the management is interested in feeding them expectations that will slightly
be beaten.
I mean that that is a world that's made to order for anybody that's trying to think
about what you do that should work over five or ten or twenty years.
And I just think that I would love to be born today and go out with not too much money and
hopefully turn it into a lot of money.
And Charlie would too actually.
He would find something to do.
I will just guarantee you.
And it wouldn't be exactly the same as before.
And he would have a big, big, big pile.
I would not like the thrill of losing my big pile into a small pile.
I like my big pile just the way it is.
Well, I like.
We agree on that incident.
Like, okay.
Yes, we do.
You're one of the most extreme lovers of the big pile.
Becky?
This question is for both Warren and Ege.
It comes from Jason Ploner in Livingston, New Jersey.
He says, "In 2016, you entered into a very unique transaction with AIG, where you assumed
up to $20 billion of liabilities in exchange for about $10 billion upfront.
Can you please provide us with an update on this transaction in light of the increase
in interest rates?"
And then in Tokyo, just a few weeks ago, you talked about the risks of banks with assets
that were susceptible to rising interest rates.
Any insight as to how Berkshire liabilities are susceptible to duration would be appreciated.
Is that directed to Ajit or me?
Both.
Okay.
Let me introduce it to my one thing.
Well, Ajit is the key to this.
He's the one that put the deal together.
But we got handed 10 billion, we'll say.
But we weren't restricted to putting that into bonds.
So what the exact interest rates affect us to some degree maybe in terms of the terms
of the deal we did with AIG or anybody we would do a similar deal with like that.
But we don't have to put it in matching bonds or anything of the sort.
It goes into a general pool of assets, which we manage in the assets.
You know, well the liquid assets now are
130 billion plus and but it goes in so it you know it
It is not set aside in some little compartment like people like to think
Now any any any other insurance no other insurance company could do it, but they can't think that way
They aren't even used to thinking that way, but they can't think that way because they don't have our our balance sheet
We account for 26% or something like that of the net worth of all property
casually companies in the United States.
So, so far, uh, the payment that we have had to make have run modestly.
And Ajit will correct me on this if I'm wrong, because he paid a lot of attention
to the, the, the, the amount we have had to pay has run slightly below the
out we anticipated having to pay in terms of our share of the losses.
But it served AIG's purposes.
It came to us with -- or we were in a unique position.
There's nobody else that was able to write that, just like when we took on the Lloyds.
I mean, Lloyds said there was no choice other than Berkshire Hathaway when they essentially
resuscitated their market by laying off a lot of liabilities on Berkshire Hathaway.
So we won't see those deals very often.
If they're for 500 million or something like that, somebody else will go in there and offer
more money.
Everybody's looking for money on Wall Street.
But if they start talking with a deal like the AIG deal, there isn't any other stop.
Correct me on all my numbers there, Ajit.
No, one way to look at how the deal is performing since we did the deal is at the point in time
when we did the deal, we had made certain projections of how much we will pay out each year.
And what we do is monitor what the actual payments are since the inception of the deal
and how does that compare with what we expected to pay out.
One mentioned these two numbers are very close to each other.
More specifically, the actual payouts are 96% of what we had projected to payout at this
point in time, which is good but not great.
We are still ahead of the curve.
If we do end up paying out less than what we projected, not only would we have borrowed
money at a very attractive rate, meaning less than 4%, significantly less than 4%.
In addition to that, we would have made a fee which in 2015 dollars would be a million
dollars.
So we would have borrowed money at less than 4% and we would have made a million dollar
fee which is slightly more than what we were expecting to do.
So Net-Net, we're very happy with the deal.
We're happy we did it.
But the game is not over.
The total liabilities are coming down the pike every second day.
So I'm cautiously optimistic that the deal will work out better than what we expected
it to work out.
Well, the really interesting thing is that within Berkshire, the casualty insurance companies
have four times as much stockholder capital behind each dollar of premium volume.
Four times normal.
And of course we see the big deals.
But would you trust if you had a big liability you wanted to dump on somebody?
And we have 25 or a billion or more coming in from things other than insurance uncorrelated
to insurance every year with no obligations.
We don't pay dividends.
If you pay dividends and you cut your dividend, try going around trying to write insurance
the next day.
And it's a business where the people are counting on you to pay.
And when we take that $10 billion, we don't agree to put it in five-year bonds and ten-year
bonds.
We don't even think that way.
And the people that do business with us know that they have somebody like nobody else on
those -- that's going to be able to pay $10 billion, you know, no matter what happens to
the economy.
So it's not only the presence of enormous strength in insurance companies, it's the
fact we got all these earnings that essentially come in every month.
And we don't have a lot of debt.
I mean, we have debt at the railroad and the energy level.
But in terms of the rest of the operation, and we don't guarantee that debt, but it's
plenty good.
And it's -- this isn't just another Berkshire, and the Jeep recognizes that when he's negotiating.
So does the other party, if the sums are big enough.
There's all kinds of people that love to get $500 million or $300 million, and they can
-- they may think in terms of lending it out because that's what their insurance companies
can do at a somewhat higher rate, but that is not a game we play in, and we don't have
any interest in playing in them.
Okay, station four.
Hello, I'm Marvin Blum, an estate planning lawyer from Fort Worth, Texas, home to many
of your companies.
In fact, Warren, I met you at the memorial for our beloved Paul Andrews, who was manager
of TTI.
I'd like to get your thoughts on a widespread problem in the world of estate planning, and
And that's the failure of most parents to prepare the next generation for the inheritance
coming their way.
In particular, if the estate includes a family business, most parents fail to do business
succession planning to plan for who will run the business on the day when, not if, the
founder is no longer there to run it.
The kids aren't prepared unlike King Charles, the other King Charles, not King Charlie Munger,
who has been preparing for his job as King of England now for more than 70 years.
I sometimes describe the situation like this, picture a football game, at one end of the
field is a quarterback, he has great skills, he throws a beautiful pass to the other end
the field, and at the other end of the field are the receivers.
They've never been to a practice.
They don't know the rules of the game.
They don't know how to work together as a team.
They're clueless.
So the quarterback is the patriarch and the matriarch.
The football is the inheritance or the family business, and the receivers are the kids.
So what are the odds that they're going to catch the football and go score a touchdown?
Probably only around 10%.
I've got the picture on the, the question.
Just kidding.
Yeah.
The, I probably observed as many just because of my age and to some extent because of things
like the giving pleasure.
I probably observed as many particularly wealthy families the problems and they all are, they
get very particular to the family.
And in my family, I do not sign a will until my three children have read it, understand
it, and made suggestions.
Now my children are in their 60s, and that would not have been a great success.
If I'd done the same thing at their 20s, it depends on the family.
It depends on how the kids feel about each other.
There's all kinds of things.
It depends on the kind of business you have.
So there's a thousand variables.
But I do think that it's,
if the children are grown and when the will is read to them,
it's the first they've heard about what the deceased
thought about things, the parents have made a terrible
mistake and people,
People, well, I've run into all kinds of situations
and some people don't tell their children anything
and some of them try and get them to defend
to their will by using their own personal will.
They make a million mistakes
and that's when you don't get to correct.
Certainly in my, well, Charlie's had a lot of experience
to it with the law.
- Well, at Berkshire we have a simple problem
of estate planning. Just hold the goddamn stock.
Well, but that doesn't fit everybody, Charlie. I mean, you know...
No, it only fits 95%.
I don't think it necessarily... I don't know, necessarily whether if you have billions of dollars you want to leave it to your children.
That's another question, but if you're ever placed somewhere, I just as soon as Berkshire
Stock is.
Yeah.
Oh, you're solving the investment problem.
But you've got the personal problem of the fact that when there were four, one of the
kids pulled the other kid's cat's tail or something like that.
I mean, you're dealing with human beings.
And the biggest thing you want is you want your children to get along.
And you want that all through your life.
And the estate isn't the only place where you can mess that up, but it's a place where
it's a very easy, I mean I know a number of cases where the people did not know what was
in the will, whether we're using something involved, and within about 15 minutes each
one of them had a lawyer, and they don't get a long sense of it.
It's important to handle it right.
And it's important if you want your kids to have a certain value, certain values, it's
important that you live those values.
It's important that you talk about it to them.
They're learning from you from the day they were born what you're really like.
And don't think that a cleverly drawn will substitute for your own behavior in teaching
your kids the values you hope that they will have.
And then your will should be in conjunction with that.
It should start expressing it.
They grow older and then they learn to pass along their values in connection with the
size of the state.
If there's family farms, it's one thing.
If there's a bunch of marketable securities, it's something else.
But I know in one instance by a particularly rich fellow that once a year, you get those
kids together and have a dinner and do all kinds of things to get them to sign their
income tax returns in blank because they didn't want them to know how much money they had
and everything.
If that isn't going to work.
I mean, I don't know what necessarily will work with him,
but if you want, you know, about Charlie and I've said it,
you know, if you want to figure out
how you want to live your life,
you write your obituary and reverse engineer it.
I mean, you know, and Paul Andrews, incidentally,
who you mentioned, that TTI lived his great life
as anybody I've known.
And he thought about these problems, and he came to me.
He was 61, I think, had all the money way beyond what he needed.
He didn't care about it.
He liked to give it to people.
He had all kinds of good things he wanted to do.
And he said, "For a year, I've been worried about my business, TTI."
And he said, "I've got all the money I need.
The family's got all the money that I need.
But what do I do with the business?"
These people have helped me throughout my life.
And he says, "I could sell it to a competitor.
If I sold it to a competitor, they'd fire my people and keep their people when they
put it together.
And if I sell it to a private equity firm or something, they'll be figuring their exit
strategy as they sign the papers.
And he said, "So I've been thinking about it a year."
And he said, "It isn't a year, such a great guy."
He says, "It's just you're the only one left."
And we bought it, and we lived happily ever after.
And that was a man that knew what life was about.
So with that, let's go on to Becky.
[APPLAUSE]
This question comes from Don Glickstein in Seattle.
He says, "Warn his criticized Norfolk Southern's handling of its train derailment, yet has
been silent about BNSF's conduct.
A federal judge ruled in March that BNSF intentionally and illegally violated an easement agreement
on tribal land in Washington state by transporting long trains of crude oil.
The same month the judge made his ruling, a BNSF train derailed on tribal land spilling
oil in an environmentally sensitive area.
What is Warren doing to ensure that BNSF and other Berkshire subsidiaries fulfill their
ethical responsibilities?
He says he's been a Berkshire owner for more than two decades, and he's concerned that
Berkshire has no systems to identify and address what he calls reprehensible behavior at BNSF
and other subsidiaries.
Greg?
Sure.
So the, it is a valid issue that our team obviously has been dealing with at BNSF.
We did move crude across that tribal land.
We had an agreement that allowed us to move X number of units per day, and we did breach
it.
We went over it.
There was some fundamental breakdowns there, and our team didn't understand the number
of trains that they could move.
We have had significant discussions with the tribe looking to resolve the issue, recognizing
We obviously benefited from moving those trains, and those type of discussions will continue.
I would say there's lessons learned there that we have to, when we make a commitment,
understand what that commitment is and live by it, or don't assume we can just move our
trains as we wish, or the cargo as we wish, we have to respect those agreements.
So there's been a moment learned there, but at the same time, we've taken it very seriously
attempted to reach a resolution there.
And at some point I hope we do come to a true resolution that's fair both to the tribe and
to BNSF.
On the derailment side, we did have an issue around the track derailed.
We worked very closely with the tribe to mitigate that issue instantly, or at least over a
very reasonable period of time.
They were very responsive.
Our team was very responsive.
And there are really no long-term environmental impacts to that spill.
And as our teams highlighted in other comments, obviously derailments do occur in the industry.
We take them incredibly serious.
They're not all hazardous, but irrespective of that.
We're constantly looking at how do we prevent them?
How do we detect them when we potentially have one that's going to occur?
and what do we do with our trains?
And then ultimately it comes down to responding properly
'cause they will occur and I think we have
an incredibly dedicated team that's always ready
to respond to the communities they're impacting.
- There are derailments, how many a year?
- Yeah, well there's a thousand plus in the industry.
- You start hauling, right, and we're a common carrier.
And we take heavy, very heavy freight,
and we take them at 100 degrees when it's the weather.
And we take it at zero.
And we go around curves, and we have grades.
And even a 1% grade, if you're going down a hill,
with, I don't know, how much weight by--
I mean, a lot of railroading is not an easy business.
And of course the systems were designed, you know, in the, in basically in the, in the
late 1800s, the mid to late 1800s.
And we have 22,000, I think it is miles of track and that doesn't count sightings and
some other things.
It is not an easy business.
We'll make mistakes.
Our job, we're not making a mistake because we have a derailment.
You're going to, we will have the derailments 10 and 20 years or 30 years from now.
I mean that, but we, and we have to carry certain products we wish we didn't have to
carry.
We're a common carrier.
Do we like carrying chlorine and ammonia and all of it?
No, but they're going to move from one place to another in this society and we are a common
carrier and we load them and if they select our railroad.
But we are better than we used to be when we got a long way to go.
Was that a fair enough statement?
Absolutely.
Yeah.
OK, station five.
Hi, Mr. Warren and Mr. Manga.
My name is Su Jinghua from China, Zhongning, Longdao,
Kamping.
And first of all, I'm so excited and very
honored to be here today.
And my question is, with more and more people focusing
on environmental protection and the government
supporting the new energy industry as well.
So what are your thoughts on the continued development
of new energy?
How may the new energy firm achieve better development
in future?
>> Yeah, well, Greg, I think it's the best answer to that
because he, since we bought a company called MidAmerican,
but now called Berkshire Hathaway Energy,
but he's been talking about it yearly, preparing reports,
hoping that we can help solve a number of the problems,
and we probably spent more money than any utility,
I would guess, in the United States.
- Absolutely.
- And we've just crashed the surface.
But it is not easy when you cross state lines.
I mean, you've got different jurisdictions,
and we should, this country should be ahead of where it is,
in terms of transmission.
We have been the biggest factor in helping that.
But why don't you tell them a little bit about it?
- Sure, thanks, Warren.
So there's no question there's an energy transformation
going on around the globe,
and as Warren touched on in the US,
and in some ways I would hope here in the US,
it would be we'd at least have a clear plan
across the nation as to how to approach that.
But the reality is it is state by state
with some exceptions.
But so as a result, when you think of Berkshire Hathaway
Energy, we own three US utilities there,
and they'll participate in multiple states.
But they're developing plans state by state,
and then trying to integrate them across the various states.
The opportunities are significant,
because there is a transformation going on.
We've outlined our goal on where we're going relative to carbon at BHE,
where they'll by 2030 reduce their carbon footprint by 50% relative to 2005.
So that's the Paris Accord and the standard they want to hold the utility industry
or the utility companies do.
And we're well on that path, but to achieve it is a true journey.
I've often talked to warm when we bought Pacific Corp back in the mid-2000s,
We immediately recognized to build a lot of renewable energy like we'd been doing in the Midwest in Iowa,
but that was basically in a single state.
Now Pacific Corp. were in six states.
We started that back in the mid-2000s.
Here we are, and we laid out a great transmission plan.
Here's how we're going to build it.
Here's how we're going to effectuate it and all the benefits for our customers over that period of time.
Here we are in 2023 and we have a little more than a third of that at the time it was a $6
billion transmission project. Today we have a little more than a third of it built and we've
spent probably closer to $7 billion and it's the right outcome. It's still a great outcome for our
customers but that transmission you absolutely as part of the transformation you absolutely have
have to build it to remove all that renewable energy.
And that's sort of the complexity Warren was highlighting.
It is a-- you can't just wake up one day and solve this problem.
You start with transmission, and then you build the resources.
But at that same company, and if we
look at what we're doing across BHE energy
and that energy transformation, we
have $70 billion of known projects
that are really required to properly serve our customers
and achieve that type of energy transformation
across those utilities.
And that's in the coming next, in the coming 10 years.
So we have a team that's absolutely up to the challenge
or delivering on their commitments.
And it's a very good business opportunity
for each of our companies and for our shareholders.
'Cause as we deploy that capital,
we obviously are in a return on equity of it.
So, but it will be a long journey.
It'll happen over an extended period of time.
And the further you get out there,
the more dependent upon the evolution
of a variety of technologies that are progressing,
but not there yet.
- You've raised a question.
I wanna just take an extra minute on it
'cause it's so important.
And I don't really know whether our form of government
is ideal at all in terms of solving the problem you describe.
We have solved it one time.
In World War II, we took a country that
was semi-limping along, and we found ourselves in a world war.
And what we did in a world war is we
brought a bunch of people to Washington at a dollar a year.
You know, whether it was Sidney Weinberg or Goldman Sachs, you just name them.
And we gave them enormous power to reorient the resources of the United States to face
the problem that they faced, which was to create a war machine.
And what they did was they found Henry Keiser, you know, and told him to build ships.
And they went to the Ford Motor Company and said, "You build tanks and some airplanes."
And they reordered the industrial enterprise of the United States in a way that was unbelievable
because they had the power of the federal government and they had the ingenuity of American
business.
And they had the facilities of American business and it led to a very successful outcome.
But can we do that in a peace time where you've got 50 states and you have to get them to
to cooperate and you don't have anyone that you can issue orders but you can't designate
where the capital goes at the other end.
We try and do it with tax incentives and all that sort of thing.
But we haven't created the unity of purpose and the machinery that worked in World War
II where essentially everybody felt their one job was to win the war and we figured
about how to use our industrial capacity to, in effect,
defeat the access powers.
And how do you recreate that with the present democratic system?
I'm not sure I know the answer, but I sure know the problem.
And I think that if you can think of a,
if you've got an emergency on your hand,
I mean, you really need to re-engineer the energy system
in the United States.
I don't think you can do it without something
resembling the machinery, the urgency, whatever.
The capital's there.
The people are there.
The objective is obvious, and we just don't seem to be able to do it in a peacetime where
we're used to following a given set of procedure.
And China, if you've got one country and we've got 50 states, and we've got a whole
different system of government, we should be up to the test, but so far it hasn't worked.
So thank you for the question.
Becky?
This question comes from Chris Freed in Philadelphia.
He says, we know that Greg Abel and Ajit Jain
are the next generation of Berkshire leaders who
are currently behind Greg and Ajit
in their perspective roles, respective.
Well, that will be the question that they give their--
Well, Greg will be at some extraordinary circumstance,
but he's going to succeed me.
And then he will be sitting in a position
where he needs his equivalent
or something close to his equivalent,
'cause he's better at many things than I've been.
He will need that substitute.
And when the question comes where, we know Ajit's opinion on that.
And -- but Greg will probably be the one that will make the final decision.
I mean, it's his responsibility.
And Ajit will give him his best advice, and I think the others are very, very, very high
that Greg would follow it.
But it's not -- those are not easy questions.
It isn't like everybody talks about the executive bench and all of that sort of thing, which
is baloney.
I mean, they don't have that many people that can run five, the largest gap net worth company
and all kinds of diverse businesses, but you don't need five people either.
And you need a lot of good operating managers and you need somebody at the top that allocates
capital and make sure that you've got the right operating manager.
And we've designed something where we separate the insurance and the rest of the business
and I think it's a very good design.
But they would not be smart.
We wouldn't be smart to name that decision now about the two different areas of the business
because a lot can change between now and then, and the most likely changes, this job changes.
Charlie?
I've got nothing to add. We have a lot of good people that have abritten in the
Berkshire subsidiaries, and there's a reason why our operations have by and large done better than
other big conglomerate companies. And one of them is that we change managers way less
frequently than other people do. And that's helped us.
When Paul Andrews died, we knew who he thought should take over there, but there wasn't any
reason to announce that. I mean, Paul Andrews would have, I wish he'd lived to be honored.
We had one of our managers die not longer going.
How old was he at the time?
Yeah, mid 90s, Seymour.
Yeah, Seymour, and we're from Seymour.
And Seymour, I wrote him a letter when he was 80
and I said, you know, I'm glad you're 80
and I'll write you again one year 90.
And I wrote him again when he was 90
and he didn't make it to 100.
But he had a terrific follow following.
following him and it really managed to jointly to some extent as the years went by, but it's
case by case.
Main thing to do is have the right person running the whole place.
Okay, station six.
Good morning.
My name's Hatch Okamoto.
I'm from Miyazaki, Japan.
I'm Mr. Buffett.
I was one of the 8,000 employees at Salomon Brothers that you saved.
I was younger back then and was working at Seven War Trade Center.
I've always, always wanted to thank you in person for saving the company, its employees,
including myself and my family.
So thank you, Mr. Buffett.
Thank you.
And thank Derek, thank Derek Maughan who actually had been over in Japan before that
And who I met for the first time the day before I put him in,
and he turned out to -- it wouldn't have --
it wouldn't have worked if Derek hadn't come.
So whatever you taught him in Japan, thank you.
>> Thank you, sir.
Now my question, time to time you have reminded us
to not bet against America.
What do you think are the most important things
for U.S. to remain strong?
And on the risk side, if the strength
of the country is undermined. What could be the reasons?
Well, we've had a lot of tests. I mean, we're such a young country. When you think about
Japan and you think about the United States, it's just incredible how new we are to the
block. I mean, what are we, 234 years old since we started? That's nothing. I mean,
Charlie and I combined, or two-thirds of the, we've lived two-thirds of the life of the country.
[laughter]
I mean, it really has, I mean, we've been tested at 46 national elections, but, and
we've made some bad choices, and we've had a civil war.
I mean, so the country has had enormous advantages, though, in some way, because we started with
one half of 1% of the world's population in 1790, and we now have something on close
25% of the world's GDP. And it wasn't because we had some incredible advantage in terms
of the land. It was nice to have two oceans on each side back when people tried to rule
the world by ruling the waves. But, you know, we had good neighbors in Canada and Mexico,
But it's a miracle.
And you say, how do we keep the good parts of the system?
While culling out our obvious defects, and we do it in a very herky-jerky manner, but
net, the United States is a better place to live than when I was born by a huge factor.
I mean, I just got a risk now a week ago, and I was just thinking, I don't know who
even Venet Novigate, but I'm for him. But in a million ways, I mean, you can romanticize
about the past, but forget it. It is work, but now we do have an atom bomb, and we wish
nuclear power. We wish the atom had never been split, but it has been, and you can't
put it back in the bottle. So the challenges are huge. Our government always looks, you
know, my dad was in Congress back in the 1940s and it looked like a mess then, you know,
although it was unified by the war to some degree, but it was still very partisan. Now
the problem we have, I think, is that partisanship, it seems to me, has moved toward tribalism.
And tribalism just doesn't work as well.
I mean, when it gets to tribalism, you don't even hear the other side.
And tribalism can lead to mobs.
I mean, it just, it flows.
I mean, you've seen it elsewhere.
We've seen it to a degree here.
So we have to refine in a certain way our democracy as we go along.
We deal with the world we live in.
But if I still had the choice of any place to be born in the world I'd want to be born
in the United States and I'd want to be born today.
I mean, it is a better world than we've ever had.
And with present day communications we can also see much more how terrible it is in many
ways.
And it's got problems.
When I was born in 1930 there were two billion people in the world.
And now there's maybe 7.7 billion and growing.
And we went millennia with really no change in population.
So we, and of course we've introduced energy into, in an incredible way, into something
where we now have 7.7 billion people using way more energy than they did when I was born
when there were 2 billion people.
So it's an exciting world.
It's a challenging world.
And I don't know the solutions on things.
I do think that we do need to think
about different solutions in terms of how
we get important problems solved and that we don't
kid ourselves that something magic will happen
or that everybody will get together and will all just
here and then go away by 2050 or anything. And how well we adapt to that. We will see.
I would say so far it doesn't look very promising, but then I'm sure that when Lincoln looked
at it, what was going on in the Civil War didn't look very promising either. So I think
that the U.S. is capable of doing remarkable things and I think it wouldn't surprise me
if they do it again.
Charlie, me, are you?
Pardon?
Well, I'm slightly less optimistic than Warren is.
I think the best road to end to human happiness
is to expect less.
I think it's going to get tougher.
And I think the solution of having a huge proportion
of the young and brilliant people all go into wealth management
is a crazy development in terms of its natural consequences
for American civilization.
We don't need as many wealth managers as we have.
You wouldn't.
Charlie was born on January 1st, 1924.
And you'd hate to go back to that, wouldn't you, Charlie?
Yes, I would.
And I like more wealth managers who are just merely
to the fact there's more wealth.
But we've got, I don't like everybody going
into wealth management, right, MIT or something.
I think the world's a little crazy now.
- Take your choice.
Okay, Becky.
- This question comes from Dennis DeGenerro.
As Warren stated in the 2022 annual report,
Berkshire will always hold a boatload of cash in U.S. Treasury bills. It will also
avoid behavior that could result in any uncomfortable cash needs at inconvenient times, including
financial panics and unprecedented insurance losses.
After Warren passes away, his A-shares will be converted into B-shares and distributed
to various foundations. These foundations will then sell the shares to fund their causes.
Warren estimates it will take 12 to 15 years for all his shares to be sold. I worry that
that a corporate raider like Cairo Icon or a group
will buy up enough of these shares
to take control of Berkshire
and completely disregard Warren's philosophy
of holding a lot of cash in US Treasury bills
and instead be greedy, reckless, and highly speculative
and ruin Berkshire's position
as a rock solid financial fortress.
I also worry that changes might be made
in how Berkshire subsidiaries are run.
Do Warren and Charlie worry that these things could happen?
- Well, I think it's fair to say we think about it plenty,
But I don't worry enormously.
If we-- and it's true that Greg and the directors will
have a honeymoon period for a long time,
because simply because of the bolts, it will still remain.
I mean, and-- but it's true that eventually they
will get judged based on how well our operation
fairs versus others.
And now if we don't pay any dividends in 12 or 15 years, you're talking a trillion and
a half that it would take to take over.
And I think if we can't, that limits the group.
They like to think about how much they can borrow against it.
It doesn't work, won't you?
And some of these, there's nobody that can come close to doing it themselves.
I think that the important thing is that Bershaw be regarded as a national asset rather than
a national liability.
We've got to be a plus to the country with our form of operation.
We certainly have got a record which will then be 12 or 15 years longer done with much
more capital, more companies.
things will have happened where our hundreds of billions can work its way into the economy
in terms of lots of jobs, lots of products, lots of behavior, and it can be compared with
other things. So I think we went out, if we deserve to
went out and I think the odds of that happening are very, very, very high.
Charlie?
Well, we -- I don't spend much time worrying about something that could happen 50 years
ago and after I'm dead.
I think if you sort of take care of each day's responsibilities pretty well and think ahead
as well as you can, and you just take the results as they fall.
So I'm Phil Salahill, but I'm not -- I need you spreading unnecessarily.
>> Okay.
Neither one of us are worried, basically.
But we -- but we plan.
We do plan.
And, you know, I've got a model in my mind of what Berkshire has been.
that model's been modified plenty of times over 58 years.
The one thing I knew initially, or very quickly,
was it shouldn't be a textile company.
That was an important decision.
And we've just played the hand as it's come along.
And we've made a few really good decisions,
and we'll never make a decision that kills us.
The only things that are a threat to the planet,
we don't have any answer for those.
But we do, we keep ourselves in better shape
than anybody else.
And we just aren't going to have big
maturities of debt that come along.
We aren't going to have insurance policies
that can be cashed in en masse.
And we will sit with a lot, what looks like
a huge amount of capital.
And it is a huge amount of capital,
but there's a huge amount of earning power.
There's a huge amount of diversity, everything.
So our business model will be graded,
and it'll be graded against a lot of people
that we'd like to be graded against.
So I think we're handling something very secure
over to the future, and I think we've got
the shareholder base like nobody has.
I mean, there isn't anybody in the country
that I know of unless they've had a shareholder
employee-owned company prior to going public
or something of the sort.
But this is the product of 58 years of regarding the shareholder as the owner of the company.
But what does that mean?
That means having happy customers.
It means being welcomed by your community rather than having them turn you away.
It means that the government feels better with you if there's a financial crisis because
year, you can provide something that actually the country can't under some circumstances,
and you'll be there.
And same time, it'll be good for the business.
And we will have crises of one sort or another, but if they aren't challenging the planet,
which worries you in terms of some of the threats that we have, we'll be a plus to the
United States and if we're opposed to the United States we'll survive.
Okay.
Station 7.
Mr. Buffett and Mr. Munger, thank you for having us this weekend.
My name is Beau Clayton and I'm from Durham, North Carolina.
One of the reasons that we are all here is that you're great storytellers, and we carry
those stories back home with us.
Can you please share a couple stories that maybe we haven't heard before about Mr. Abel
and Mr. Jane that captured their character and their caliber as leaders.
[ Applause ]
>> I'll start out with the G. He walked into the office in 1986,
and I had gotten the bright idea of going
into the reinsurance business, I think it may be 1969.
So I'd stumbled along for 17 years,
and I had a wonderful guy that ran it.
But he also liked certain brokers.
And I mean, he was running it the traditional way,
the top quality and everything else.
But he didn't try and change the system.
He tried to improve the system to some degree.
And we just went nowhere.
17 years wandering around in the wilderness,
and I thought I knew we could have something good.
And then Ajit came in on a Saturday.
And Mike Goldberg and Steerdiam, I think.
And Mike deserves to be enshrined
and perpetuity for that act.
And I talked with him a while.
I think maybe I was opening the mail on Saturday
while I talked with him.
And he had absolutely zero experience with insurance,
but he'd actually seen a good bit
of how corporate America operated
because he'd been in management consulting.
And after talking with him,
I knew I'd struck gold and so I hired him and gave him the backing of some money.
And we had a very good period in the market, almost right away for him to act and to cheat.
You know, if I had the top pick of 10 insurance managers in the world, I could take all 10.
And they wouldn't, you can't replace Ajit.
And we still enjoy talking.
We don't talk as frequently as we used to, but we used to talk about it every day.
But he is one of a kind.
And you know, if they're going to stick around long enough, you only need one of a kind.
Paul Andrews stuck around at TTI, had all the money in the world.
Every time I talk to him about getting a raise or something of the sort, he said, "We'll
talk about that next year."
He was not what you get when you get the top draft picks from the leading business schools.
I will say this, I have never looked at where anybody went to school in terms of hiring.
Somebody mailed me a resume or something.
I don't get where they went to school.
It just so happens that Achille went to some pretty good schools, but he isn't Achille
because he went to the schools.
And, uh, Charlie didn't tell a story or two.
How'd you find Louis Bencenny?
Well, he was there.
But you got to recognize him.
I asked Louis once how he managed to play first-string football at, I think, Stanford,
the only way to hundred and fifty-five pounds. And he said, "Well," he said, "I was pretty
quick." And he was pretty quick, but we have found a lot of people within our companies
who were pretty quick. It's a...
Yeah, we had one guy that quit at fourth grade in Ben Rosner. Am I wrong?
Oh, yeah. Totally self-educated. Ben Rosner knew more about retailing and difficult neighborhoods
and anybody and he watched everything in his business like a hawk and he was amazing.
Now there was an example, we never found anybody who could do what, when Ben died,
that ability left us.
>> Yeah, and you want a story, it's kind of interesting because Ben Rosner had a partner,
Leo Simon. And at least Leo Simon was Moana Burke's son-in-law and Leo, therefore, was
very, very, very wealthy and then started with nothing, but they liked each other. And
One time, well before they got involved in the business we bought,
but they got the idea of buying a submarine from World War I
and taking it to the Century of Progress,
which was the world's far end effect in Chicago, I think, in 1933.
So they bought the submarine for probably nothing.
And they figured, you know, the average guy from Omaha
was going to his first world's fair,
get into a submarine for a quarter or something,
that they'd pay it.
So they hauled it from Florida, wherever they got.
They hauled it to Chicago,
and then they got into Chicago.
And they were hauling a submarine down the streets
of Chicago, and it was creating traffic problems,
like nobody could imagine.
So a cop came over and he said to Ben,
he says, "Where do you think you guys
"are going with a submarine?"
Ben says, "Well, you'll have to talk to my partner,
"Mr. Cawone."
(laughing)
The cop says, "You're on, just keep going."
And that was Ben Rosner.
And then Leo Simon died.
And when he died in 1967 or so,
Ben Rosner kept the ring half the profits to his widow, who was incredibly rich, of
course, being Moe Annenberg's first-born daughter.
I think Moe had nine girls in a row before Walter came along, the tenth, I may be lost
by one.
I went to this fancy apartment and anyway, Ben kept her in for half the deal and he
had her sign the rent checks just so she would look like she was doing something in this
business.
And she didn't need the money obviously, but he just felt he was obligated once his partner
and Leo died.
And then she started criticizing him.
And at that point, Ben went to her, his lawyer,
or his lawyer, actually, Will Feldsteiner,
when whatever happened to Will,
but he gave me a call because Ben wanted to call me
because he wanted me to buy it.
And he wanted me, if I bought it,
he'd be rid of the ex-partner's wife.
And he'd get, he had me and Charlie come back
and we went to Will Feldsteiners office
and Beds says I'll work 'til the end of the year
and that's all.
But I'll show you this thing for six million bucks
and I had two million to cash and a couple million
to real estate and a couple million to operating earnings.
That was just crazy.
But he felt if he was getting a lousy price,
she was taking a half of, a lousy price for half the money.
So he looked at me at some point.
Charlie, you describe the rest of it.
Look at it again.
- He said, "I heard here the fastest draw in the west."
He says, "Draw."
(laughing)
- We're in the New York Lawyer's office.
- Yeah.
- And this guy is selling his baby
and he told us he was leaving.
I got Charlie on the side.
I said, "If this guy leaves at the end of the year,
"you can throw away every psychology book
has ever been written. I mean, it isn't going to happen. And so we bought it and we lived
happily ever after with Ben. And one time he was taking me over to see a property we had
in Brooklyn. And along the way I said, "Ben, I promised you I wouldn't interfere in the
business when we started." And he knew a butt was coming and he just said, "Thank you,
And they shut me up.
[laughter]
He was a lot of fun.
We have so many Ben Rosner stories, but now you've heard one that hasn't been published
before.
Okay, Becky.
>> This question comes from Chai Gohill.
He writes, "This is for a cheap.
Re-insurance industry is going through one of the hardest pricing environments in the
last 15 years.
Berkshire historically has participated during these stress times when economic returns are
very attractive.
This year it appears Berkshire has not been interested in deploying its resources towards
property/cat reinsurance despite such strong returns.
Can you elaborate on reasons for not participating despite these returns and your broader view
on how you're planning to shape your reinsurance business post-acquisition of Allegheny?
Okay.
In terms of Allegheny, that's an easy response.
We treat operating units independent of each other.
And as far as Allegheny is concerned, they have a major presence in the re-insurance
business under the brand name of Transatlantic Reef.
That company will operate the way it's been operating in the past.
There will be no change in terms of strategy or management.
And they will keep doing what they're doing.
They'll be very successful and hopefully they'll keep being successful.
Now, in terms of the property cat business that I have been active in over these last
several years, you are right that the last 15 years has been a difficult time, prices
have not been attractive.
And even though we have had some presence in the property cat business in the last 15
years, it really is being minimal.
This December 31st, which is a big renewal date for cat re-insurance, we were hoping
that we would get a few days in the sun and we'd be able to deploy our capital and be
able to write some fairly attractive business.
As it happened towards the end of December, till about the third week of December, I was
very optimistic that we would get a chance to put several billion dollars on the books.
But in the last 10 days of December, unfortunately a lot of capacity came out of the woodworks
pricing that we were expecting to realize didn't really come and meet our
pricing requirements as a result of which January 1 was a big disappointment.
We did not write as much as we were hoping to write. Now fast forward to
April 1 which is another big renewal date. We had a lot of powder dry and we
were lucky that we kept the powder dry because April 1 suddenly prices zoomed
up again a lot higher than what they were on January 1 and started to look
attractive to us. So now we have a portfolio that is very heavily exposed to
property catastrophe. To put that in perspective, our exposure today is almost
50% more than what it was five, six months ago. So you know, we I think we
have written as much as our capacity will allow us to write. We are very happy
happy with what we've written, the margins have been healthy.
The only thing that I want to mention to you is that while the margins have been healthy,
we have a very unbalanced portfolio.
What that means is if there's a big hurricane in Florida, we will have a very substantial
loss as opposed to that if we have a very big loss anywhere other than Florida.
to our competition, we will have a much smaller loss.
Net-net, I'm very happy with the portfolio.
It's been a lot better.
It is a lot better than what it's been in the past.
I don't know how long it will last.
And of course, if the hurricane happens in Florida,
we could lose-- across all the units,
we could lose as much as $15 billion.
And if there isn't a loss, we'll make several billion dollars
his profit.
And G, tell him how long, when you call me and said you'd like to expose us to whatever
was a couple billion more of exposure, how long I took to say yes.
Yeah.
So the way we think about our exposures, you know, in the property, in the insurance operations
collectively across the entire company, given that we have about a little less than 300
billion of capital, we think of that as a 55% exposure that you're willing to take on.
So to complete Warren's story, a few weeks ago we had about $13 billion of exposure all
across the globe.
And I called up Warren, I said, "We have to 13, it'll be nice if we can go up to 15,
that's a good round number."
And that was less than a 30 second phone call.
I think Warren said yes without even listening to what the numbers were.
I hope he calls me again.
Okay, station eight.
Hello.
My name is Adal Flores and I've been a shitholder for about 16 years and I'm coming from Guadalajara,
Mexico.
My question is for Warren and Charlie.
Companies have the eternal dilemma between building products that can make profits and
increase their company competitive position.
In the best case, you can build products that have both characteristics at the same time
like Google did.
But most of the time, companies need to choose between short-term profits and long-term defensibility.
For example, Amazon was focused on building their famous Amazon flywheel with limited
profit it initially in order to obtain stronger network effects with the hope of getting more
defensible profits in the future.
When you invest, you constantly speak about the importance of building competitive modes.
What advice would you give to CEOs about how to balance this dilemma, which is essentially
short-term profit versus long-term defintibility?
Thank you.
Well, the answer is to control your destiny, which we've been able to do at Berkshire.
So we feel no pressure from Wall Street.
We don't have investor calls.
We don't have to make promises.
We get a chance to make our own mistakes and occasionally find something that works well.
But we recognize that the people in this room and people like them are the ones we're working
for and we're not working for a bunch of people that care about whether we meet the
court or estimate or anything so that we have a freedom that we get to use and we're interested
in owning a wonderful business forever.
Well, there aren't very many wonderful businesses, but we do learn a lot as we go along.
Charlie and I have often mentioned how we learned so much when we bought C's candy,
which we did.
But we learned when we bought Ben Roser's chain of women's dress shops, spread all over
the eastern part of the country.
We learned when we tried getting into the department store business back in 1966.
As the ink was drying on our purchase price, we realized we'd done something dumb.
We're learning all the time how consumers behave.
I'm not going to be able to learn the technical aspects of businesses, but that'd be nice
if I knew it.
But it isn't essential.
And you know, we are obviously, we've got a business at Apple which is larger than our
energy business and we may only own 5.6 or 7%, but our ownership goes up every year and
I don't understand the phone at all, but I do understand consumer behavior and I know
I know how people think about whether to buy a second car.
I know how they go out to different,
we own auto dealerships, we're earning all the time
from all of our businesses, how people react to granite
versus selling them something else.
And so C's was a sort of breakthrough,
but we just keep learning as to more about
how people behave and how a good business can turn into a bad business and how some
good businesses can maintain their competitive advantage over time.
So we don't have some formula.
But we can also tell in 10 seconds whether it's something of interest.
I mean, when I get these calls and we want to send decks and all that sort of thing,
which is nonsense.
I mean, it's a bunch of guys sitting and get paid for growing up these projections of the
future and everything like that.
If they knew the future, we don't know the future, but we do know certain kinds of businesses.
We know what the right price is and we know what we think we can project out in terms
of consumer behavior and consumer threats to a business.
That's what we've been about and that's what we'll continue to be about.
We do get, we don't get smarter over time.
We get a little wiser though, following it over time and you can do it while sitting
in the office with a telephone too, which we like. Charlie?
- Well, tell them the story of the Japanese investment.
That should be told again.
That's a nice story.
- Well, it was pretty simple.
Back when I started, other people were going through Playboy
and I was going through Moody's basically.
There's a movie out called Turn Every Page,
which I saw again for the second time a couple of days ago,
Lizzie Gottlieb, and I recommend everybody in this world
watch that because I turned every page in the past.
And I did it for thousands and thousands of pages in Moody's
and I did it at the Department of Public Utilities
and in Boston, I did it at the Insurance Department.
You just kept turning pages.
Well, that goes on for a while.
But now we need big ideas in order to find things.
And what was your question, Charlie?
- Did you tell them about the Japanese?
- Well, the Japanese thing was simple.
I mean, I like looking at companies.
I mean, I like looking at figures about companies.
And here were five very, very substantial companies,
understandable companies.
Most of them, maybe all of them,
we'd done business with in a dozen different ways.
If you go a couple miles from where this place is,
our last coal generating plant was built
by one of the companies.
So here they were, they were sitting as a group
where they were earning, we'll say 14%
on what we were gonna pay to buy them.
They were paying decent dividends,
they were going to repurchase shares in some cases.
They owned a whole bunch of businesses
that we could understand as a group,
although we didn't mean we had deep understanding
on anything, but we seen them operating everything.
There wasn't anything to it.
And at the same time, we could take out the currency risk
by financing in the end,
and that was going to cost us a half of 1%.
Well, if you get 14% on one side,
a half a percent on the other side,
And you've got money that, you know, forever,
and they're doing intelligent things and they're sizable.
So we just started buying them.
I didn't even probably tell Greg until maybe six months
after we'd gotten going.
And then when we hit 5%, in all of them,
we announced on my birthday at 90th,
that we owned over 5%.
and recently went over for the first time
to visit with them and we were more than pleasantly surprised,
delighted with what we find there.
And now we own 7.4% of it.
We won't go over 9.9% without their agreeing
and we sold another 164, whatever it is.
Billion of a, again.
- What have done for us if we only had five billion
dollars or something and it made ten billion dollars simply in that way.
Yeah.
We would look like heroes.
Now ten billion just sort of disappears as a little dot in Bertrand's reports.
But it's fun.
And it is fun and it is ten billion dollars.
And Charlie says it keeps me out of bars.
I probably talked to him about it.
I probably talked to Charlie about this the year after I started.
But who knows? I mean, I knew he'd like it. I mean, obviously. And we tried to do every
dollar we could do. We could only do about ten billion.
Yeah. Well, not even that, quite that much. But, you know, we are four or five billion
ahead plus dividends, and we got to carry this terrific. And, you know, and they welcome
us, and they should welcome us. But we love it the way they're operating. We're not there
to tell them what to do in the least.
So we did, but we did say we'd never go over 9.9 and we made it.
They know that we'll be true to our word.
I went over there partly to introduce Greg to those people because we're going to be
with them 10, 20, 30, 40 years from now.
And they may occasionally find something that we can do jointly.
And they look forward to doing that.
And we look forward to it.
And in addition, we have some other operating businesses in Japan.
So, Greg, do you have anything?
The only thing I would add is that one, as Warren you went over there, it was to build
the trust with these Japanese companies because we do hope there's long-term opportunities.
But fundamentally, as you highlighted, they're an incredible -- they've been a very good
investment.
I'd also highlight the five meetings we had.
We're really quite remarkable.
I mean, these companies, the culture and the history
around it and how proud they are, you know,
there's just moments of learning from them.
So it was just a great experience to spend really two days
with the five companies.
>> And an issue that we intended to be 56 billion of yen
that we were issuing and selling turned out to be 164.4,
something like that.
Everything works so well, and as Charlie says it,
it doesn't move 500 billion of net worth that much.
But this one, it will keep adding over the years
to Berkshire's value with this very wide spread,
probably four or 500 million dollars a year.
And we'll just keep looking for more opportunities.
And Japan, we have, Berger is the largest borrower outside
of corporate borrower, outside of Japan that exists.
And we didn't set out to be that.
It's turned out that way.
And we're not done.
I mean, in terms of what may come along there,
and we have some direct operations there,
as I mentioned, and we've got some really wonderful partners working for us, and I don't
have to do anything.
Okay, Becky.
>> The next question comes from Ellie Amin Tibet, who asks, "During an episode of 'Investing
the Templeton Way' podcast, Professor Damodaran, who he respects almost as much as Warren and
Charlie mentioned that he is not comfortable with positions becoming a large part of his
portfolio. For example, when they reached 25 to 35 percent, he mentioned that Apple is
now 35 percent of Berkshire's portfolio and thinks that that is near a danger zone. Wonders
if Warren and Charlie can comment.
I'll leave him in one comment first, but Charlie will come up with-
I think he's not always one.
I knew that was coming.
(audience laughing)
But, Apple is not 35% of Berkshire's portfolio.
Berkshire's portfolio includes the railroad,
the energy business, gradables, you name it, Sees Candy.
They're all businesses.
And, you know, the good thing about Apple
is that we can go up.
They buy in their stock and instead of owning 5.6%,
You know, they got down to, they got about 15 billion,
700 and some million shares outstanding.
They got down to 15 and a quarter billion
without us doing anything.
We got 6%.
So we can't own more than 100% of the world.
BNSF, we can't own more than 100% of ground animals
or seized candy.
And it'd be nice, we'd love to own 200% but that just
is doable.
But they're all the same.
They're good businesses.
And to think that our criterion, our criteria for Apple
is different than the other businesses we own.
It just happens to be a better business than any we own.
And we put a fair amount of money in it,
but we haven't got more money in it
than we've got in the railroad.
And Apple is a better business,
our railroad is a very good business,
but it's not remotely as good as Apple's business.
Apple has a position with consumers where they're paying,
maybe they'll pay 1500 bucks or whatever it may be
for a phone and these same people pay $35,000
for having a second car.
And if they had to give up a second car
or give up their iPhone, they'd give up their second car.
I mean, it's an extraordinary,
probably we don't have anything like that
that we own 100% of,
but we're very, very, very happy to have 5.6
or whatever it may be, percent.
And we're delighted at every tenth of a percent
that goes up.
That's like adding $100 million to our earnings.
I mean, our share of the earnings.
And they use their earnings to buy out our partners,
which we're glad to see them sell out too.
The index funds have to sell out.
They bring the number of shares down.
And, you know, we went up slightly last year
And I made a mistake a couple of years ago
and I sold some shares when I had certain reasons why
gains were useful to take that year from a tag standpoint.
But having heard me say that, it was a dumb decision.
Charlie, you've already given your comment about it,
But we do not have 35% of Berkshire's portfolio.
Berkshire's portfolio is the funds we have to work with.
And we want to own good businesses,
and we also want to have plenty of liquidity.
And beyond that, the sky's the limit,
or our mistakes, who knows what the bottom is.
Charlie, do you want to add anything to your earlier comment?
Well, I think one of the inane things that's
taught in modern university education
is that a vast diversification is absolutely mandatory
and investing in common stocks.
That is an insane idea.
It's not that easy to have a vast plethora of good opportunities
that are easily identified.
And if you've only got three, I'd rather
every of my best ideas instead of my worst.
And now some people can't tell their best ideas
from their worst and in the act of deciding
that the investment already is good,
they get to thinking it's better than it is.
I think we make fewer mistakes like that than other people.
And that is a blessing to us.
We're not so smart, but we kind of know
where the edge of our smartness is.
That is a very important part of practical intelligence.
And a lot of people who are geniuses on IQ tests
think they're a lot smarter than they are.
And what they are is dangerous.
And, but if you know the edge of your own ability pretty well,
you should ignore most of the notions of our experts
about what I call "deworcification of portfolios."
- Okay.
(audience applauding)
- Session nine.
- Hi, Charlie and Warren.
Thank you for this superb shareholder meeting celebration.
My name is David Chung from Hong Kong
and a proud graduate of Chicago Booth.
I'm also here with my two sons, Aidan and Ashen,
who's currently studying University of Chicago
as a freshman and sophomore.
This is my second time attending the conference,
last being 2019, four years ago,
which I was only a guest shareholder of my friend Andrew.
So after the shareholder meeting,
I have decided to buy into Berkshire Halfway,
which has given me a great return of 62% since 2009.
So I want to thank you for that.
(audience applauding)
I have also taken one of your advice
to give my children a share for each of their birthdays.
Although they won a Berger half away A shares,
(audience laughing)
they will do just fine with B shares.
My question is, how do you see the current US, China, internet companies valuation and
the price disparity?
Given there has been many uncertainties such as geo, political tensions, significant cost
optimizations with leaner US tech firms, while China tech has been through all that already.
Thank you.
Charlie, I want to -- well, there's been some tension in the economic relationship of
United States and China.
I think that tension has been wrongly created on both sides.
I think we're equally guilty of being stupid.
There's one thing we should do.
Let's get along with China, and we should have a lot of free trade with China in our
mutual interest.
I just can't imagine.
It's just so obvious.
There's so much safety and so much creativity that's possible.
what Apple has done by engaging in a partnership with China as a big supplier.
It's been good for Apple and good for China.
That's the kind of business we ought to be doing with China.
And more of it.
Everything that increases the tension between the two companies is stupid, stupid, stupid.
And it ought to be stopped on each side.
And each side ought to respond to the other side's stupidity with reciprocal kindness.
That's my view.
And it creates one enormous problem, of course, which is that you have the two superpowers
of the world, and they know they have to get along with each other.
Either one can destroy the other, and they're going to be competitive with each other.
But part of it is trying always in a game like that, is trying to judge how far you
can push the other guy without them reacting wrong.
And you know, if either side is a bully in some way, they can get away with it to an
extent because the alternative is, would drive them both into destruction.
But if they push it too far, they increase the probability that something really does
go wrong.
So it's, you know, it's one of those game theory dilemmas.
But you really need the leader of both countries.
And you need the populace to understand at least the general situation in which these
countries are going to operate over the next century, and know that some leader that promises
too much can get you in a hell of a lot of trouble.
And that, like, you know, you've got one kind of a system that gets its leader one way and
you've got another system that gets its leader another way.
And keeping either side from trying to play the game too hard and thinking the other side
will go along. It's like playing chicken and driving toward a cliff. So it is, if you've
got any diplomacy skills, persuasive skills, or anything like that, you really want people
that will convince the other country as well as her own country that this is what we're
engaged in, we've got to do it right. We won't give away the store, but we won't
try and take the whole store either. We're just at the beginning of this,
unfortunately. I mean, we learned what the situation was. It used to be the
Soviet, and the mutually assured destruction was our policy then, and
And that kept a lot of things from happening, but it also came with a very, very, very close
call with Cuba.
And these are not, you know, these are different games than existed hundreds of years ago.
You could, you know, Britain might rule the seas, or France, or Spain, but now you're
playing with a game that you can't really make a huge mistake in.
And I think that that should be the better that's understood in both countries.
The more the leaders feel that their citizenry does understand that, the better off will
be.
A lot of demography, a lot of inflammatory speaking, but a lot of authoritarian action.
I mean, it all carries its dangers.
The world was stumbled through the years post-1945
with a lot of close calls from the, in the nuclear arena.
And now we've got pandemics and we've got,
we've got cyber and a whole bunch of other things.
So we've got more tools of destruction
than the world's ever had.
And it's imperative that China and the United States
and the United States both understand what the game is
and understand that you can't push too hard,
but both places are gonna be competitive
and both can prosper.
That's what really is, that's the vision
that is out there that China will have
a more wonderful country, the United States
will have a more wonderful country
And the two are not just compatible.
They're almost imperative in terms of what's
going to happen in the next 100 years or so.
And I think that the leaders of both countries
have got an important job in having that understood
and not to do inflammatory things.
And we'll see whether the lock that has taken us from 1945
to present holds out.
And I think we can affect, to some extent, that lock.
And with that sherry message, we will hold it to Becky.
This question comes from Rohit Bellany.
Berkshire bought a substantial position in Taiwan semiconductor
and contrary to its normal holding timeline,
sold almost the entire position within a few short months.
While you cited in a CNBC interview that geopolitical issues were the catalyst, these
issues were seemingly no different when you acquired that stock.
So what else, if anything, changed in those few months and prompted the firm to offload
close to $5 billion worth of Taiwan semiconductor shares?
Taiwan semiconductor is one of the best managed companies and important companies in the world.
And there is not, and I think you'll be able to say the same thing five or ten or twenty
years from now.
I don't like its location and I've re-evaluated that.
I mean I don't think there should be any place but Taiwan although they will be obviously
opening up ship capacity in this country.
And actually one of our subsidiaries that we got in Allegheny is participating in their
Arizona construction activities.
But it's a question of we would rather have the same kind of company.
There's nobody in the chip company, there's nobody in the chip industry that's in their
league in our, at least in my view.
And the man that was a 91 year old or so that connected with it that I think I played Bridge
with and Albuquerque.
And the marvelous people, marvelous company, but I'd rather find a marvelous people, I
I won't find it in the ship industry,
but marvelous people and marvelous competitive position
and everything, I'd rather find it in the United States.
I feel better about the capital that we've got deployed
in Japan than in Taiwan.
I wish I weren't so, but I think that's a reality
and I've reevaluated that in the light of certain things
that were going on.
Charlie?
My view is that we're not feel comfortable if you want to.
[ Laughter ]
Put that in the minutes.
Okay, station 10.
>> First of all, thank you for making our lives better.
My name is Bogumil Baranowski.
I'm a founding partner of SIKAS Associates in New York.
We manage multi-generational family fortunes,
hence my question.
Mr. Buffett, in 1976, in your tribute to Benjamin Graham,
you wrote, "Walter Lippmann spoke of men
"who plan trees that other men will sit under.
"Ben Graham was such a man.
"You're both such people.
"Could you share with us your 100-year vision for Berkshire?"
It's a question to you both.
Yeah, I would like to add one thing about Ben Graham.
Ben Graham did all kinds of things for me.
I never expected one thing in return.
I mean, just you name it, and he did it, and there wasn't any hidden, you know, a hint,
I should say, of anything he expected in return.
And I checked, well he wrote a book in 1949 that in a sense said to me in very persuasive
terms that what I had been spending the previous eight or nine years working at and loving
was all wrong.
And that book has been, I check it every now and then on Amazon to where it ranks, and
you know, Amazon ranks hundreds and hundreds and hundreds of thousands of books by sales.
And Ben Graham's book has been up there like number 300 or 350 or something like that forever.
And there isn't any book like that.
I wrote Harper Collins and Know The Other Day
'cause they're bringing out another edition.
And I asked them how many copies have been sold
and they said the records didn't go back far enough
but they had 7.3 million copies of this little book
that changed my life and continues to outsell
every investment book.
Investment comes along and they're number 400 or 1,000
or something for a while
and then all of a sudden they're number 25,000 or 200,000.
And this book, in how many areas can you find any book
that has had that sustained position?
You go back and look at number one at 1950
or number two or number three
and you look at them 51 and 52.
They don't continue.
I mean, they just don't continue.
Cookbooks, maybe one or two of them last for a while,
but there is nothing.
And this book lives on and everybody keeps bringing out
new books and saying a lot of other things,
but they aren't saying anything that's as important
as what he said in 1949 in this relatively thin little book.
So, our vision for Berkshire is to get
For Berkshire, this is exactly what we said today.
We want it to be a company that is owned by its shareholders and behaves in a way that
society is happy that it exists and not unhappy.
And we will have unlimited capital.
We'll get lots of talent.
And we've got a base that can't be beat.
And there's no reason why it can't be perpetuated just like Ben's book and maybe be an example
to other people.
And if so, we'll be very happy.
Charlie?
Yeah, one of the really interesting things about Ben and Gary, he was a really gifted
teacher, a very honorable profession.
And that is what has lasted.
However, an interesting fact that he was sheepish about in his old age was that more than half
of all the investment return that Benningram made in his whole life came from one stock,
one growth stock, GEICO, Berger's subsidiary.
And at the time he operated, there were a lot of sort of lousy companies that were too
cheap and you could make a little money floating from one to another. But the big money he
made was one growth stock. Buying one undervalued great company is a very good thing as Berkshire
has found out again and again and again.
And Ben wrote a post-crypt of the '49 edition pointing out exactly that fact and acknowledging
it but also took some good lessons from it.
That's the way life is, that you prepare and you don't lose everything along the way.
And then something comes along.
And Geico came along because a banker in Fort Worth that had financed Leo Davison, and I
think the banker got three quarters of it, and I don't mean Leo Davison, Leo Goodwin,
founded Geico, then called Government Employees Insurance Company, and you can figure out the
acronym. And the deal almost fell apart. The deal was, as I remember, maybe a million
and a half or something like a million and a quarter. And it almost fell apart because
of a difference of $25,000 in the net worth delivered. This is a business that's, you
You know, we're tens of billions.
But he pointed out the irony in that too.
I mean, he was honest about,
he was totally intellectually honest about his,
the failings and also the strengths of his approach.
And that to some extent, you know,
Charlie and I have seen that in our lives.
I mean, sort of the prepared mind,
the willingness to act when you need to act
and the willingness to ignore every salesman in the world
and imperative to ignore them.
And it's one or two things that make the right decision.
If you make the right decision on a spouse,
I mean, you've won the game.
And there's enormous important decision
and you got all the time.
I mean, in the world, you got more time now
than you used to have when I was kid
to make that decision.
And I don't know whether a third or whatever percentage
blow that one.
It is really interesting.
The thing to do is just keep trying to think things through
and not do too many stupid things.
And sooner or later, you'll have a lot of plows,
as Shirley would say.
OK, Becky.
>> All right, this question comes from Tarafter,
a shareholder in Sierra Vista, Arizona,
who is asking a question of a jeep.
He wants to know about electric vehicles getting insurance
from the manufacturer instead of car insurance companies.
A recent article in the Wall Street Journal shows
that the EVs are a small but growing percentage of sales.
Tesla and GM are offering their own electric vehicle insurance.
What will GEICO do to combat this?
Yeah, so Geico is talking to a number of original equipment
manufacturers as well to try and see how best they can work
with the auto manufacturer and offer insurance
at the point of sale.
There haven't been very many success stories as yet.
So we'll wait and see.
Clearly, it is a very convenient way
to sell auto insurance at the point of sale.
But there's a fair amount of data
that needs to be collected on the driver, not just the car.
And that makes it a little more complicated.
So we are talking to some auto manufacturers ourselves.
We are hopeful too that we will strike a deal with some of them
before not too long.
Tesla has made the--
and GM, they both have talked a lot in the press in terms
of getting into their insurance business.
And in fact, GM, I think, has projected.
They'll write $3 billion of premium,
which, you know, it's hard to imagine where it'll come from.
But they're all hard to trot.
I think somebody will find the secret sauce
before not too long and we ourselves are in that race.
- Yeah, I would point out that General Motors
had Motors insurance for decades.
And I mean, this is not a new idea.
And Uber,
Uber, no lot of insurance for a while, they laid it off with somebody and that company
got killed by it, and I don't know the deal between Uber and, forget the name of the company
that took it on, Jeet would probably know, but...
James River.
Yeah, and you know, there's nothing, it's not a new idea, it's not magic in the least.
I mean, it is hard to come up with something that is better
at missing and matching risk to reward,
I'm sorry, risk to prize.
Then a bunch of very smart people are doing it,
a progressive and a bunch of very smart people
are doing it to a greater extent at Geico.
And I mean, it is, it just,
It was fascinating to me when Uber went into it, you know,
and they were going to get their head handed to them,
but they laid off a good bit of it,
a very substantial percentage of it was somebody else
who got their head handed to it.
And, you know, but it was a story, you know,
Wall Street loves it.
We've got 80 car dealerships that do a lot of business.
And, you know, we've got the people buying the car
and the place and we form an insurance company around the
dealer group for some reason that writes insurance.
You know, it's hard to improve on the present system.
>> Yeah.
>> I have no -- I wouldn't pay a penny.
I'd pay to avoid it actually.
I mean, and go ahead, Ajit.
>> Yeah, the only point I'd like to add is the margins
on writing auto insurance are 4%, which is a very small number.
And once there are more people that are trying to take a bite of the apple, it just becomes
very, very difficult to keep all the mouths fed in a profitable manner.
>> Now, you can say that there was one big new idea in insurance and car insurance back
in 1920 or so when State Farm started.
State Farm and still has it next to Berkshire. It's the leader in having that worth. It's
a mutual company, but some guy just figured that there was a cartel running car insurance
and he, farmer from Urna, the name of the book I think, over in Illinois, he created
a system where you really took 20 points or so out of the costs. And surprise, surprise
areas. You know, and nobody's own stock and state farm. It's an insult to capitalism,
actually. Everything you learn at the business school says it shouldn't work because nobody
owns it, nobody's going public with it, no nothing. But it's got more net worth. It's
almost probably double leaving Berkshire in the picture. It's probably double the next
guy and nobody's really improved on their system that much.
So it's fascinating how people don't really look at the essence.
These are cases that should carry a message.
But the truth is in Wall Street, anything that gets -- the test is whether you can sell
it or not.
If you can sell it, it will get sold.
And a bunch of insurance companies came along and got it sold, and this can be a story about
this stock or that stock.
And it sounded good when they talked about it at Uber for a while.
It is really interesting.
The investing public does not learn much.
Okay, station 11.
>> Hi, my name is Jeff Merriam.
I'm from Edina, Minnesota.
You've been coming for years to make that professor from the earlier question really nervous.
Half our family's wealth is in Berkshire Hathaway.
Well, that doesn't make Charlie nervous.
My question has to do with voting control in the future.
There was a question earlier about corporate raider.
I was more wondering about who is actually going to own the voting control.
Is it going to be institutions, CalPERS, BlackRock?
Are they eventually going to get their way with the ESG checkboxes that we're going to
have to check?
And what should we be thinking about that?
Well, you're thinking very well.
And the interesting thing is the big aggregations look like, of course, they'd be in index funds.
But what index funds want is they want a world in which society doesn't get upset with them
about the fact that I've got all the voting power.
And I would say in the last year or two,
it's looked like a better idea for them not quite together.
What was the phrase that Charlie used?
I've been...
- They backed off a lot.
- Yeah, they backed off a lot.
And they're interested to back out often.
Interestingly enough,
And looking at money management, you know, the game is not performance, it's assets
under management.
And index funds produce a tiny, tiny, tiny fee on assets under management because it
was pioneered by Vanguard.
And it's -- when it became successful, it was very easy to replicate.
not so easy, but I mean it was inevitable that it would be copied.
But it came with a management fee of two basis points.
So what people that have offered index funds would really like is you to buy their other
funds or let them manage money in some other way so that they get a higher fee on assets
under management.
which of course is exactly why the index fund was invented in the first place.
But so it's gotten, it's not a lost leader, but it is a way to pull money in.
And then you hope that people ignore what was said by, by, what's the name that, you know,
that John Bogal, Jack Bogal, ignore him. And essentially they give up the idea and that
We'll offer you a fund that does this in India,
and we'll offer you another fund that does that,
and of course those management fees are higher.
So they're really counter selling the idea
that John Bogle came along with.
But in the process, they have achieved a lot of votes,
and that was fun for a while,
but the last thing in the world I wanted to do
is have Washington, or the American public,
decide that they're throwing around their weight too much.
So they're tending to back off now.
If you figure out where their self-interest is,
you can judge where their behavior is going to go.
Charlie, you want to defend them?
- No, you can swear at me while you just said.
(laughing)
You're totally right on everything.
- Well, in that case, I won't ask anybody else.
Okay, Becky?
(laughing)
- All right, this question comes from Almu Grinnell,
And it's about, this is for Warren and Greg.
Since 2019, Berkshire repurchased huge amounts of stock
about approximately reducing 10% of the share count
and increasing the intrinsic value per share
for the continuing shareholders.
Greg is expected to be the successor of Warren as CEO,
so will he be in charge of the main
capital allocation decisions,
including future share buybacks?
Greg has been key in the development
of Berkshire Hathaway Energy,
and I think a good capital allocator.
Has he been involved in the share repurchases that have been executed over the past years?
And do you, both Warren and Greg, work together in the estimation of Berkshire's intrinsic
value and the share buyback decisions?
Well, the answer is that Greg -- I'm going to turn it over to him, but the answer is
Greg understands capital allocation as well as I do, and that's lucky for us.
And he will make those decisions, I think, very much in the same framework as I would
and make them.
And we've laid out that framework now for 30 years
or something like that.
People make it way more complicated.
I mean, particularly if you're working on a doctorate
or something, it's just a great subject
to have lots of footnotes and 50 pages or 100 pages.
But it's no more complicated than if you and I
and Charlie had a business and you wanted to sell
your interest and we could buy it for less
than we thought it was worth.
and without misleading you in any way about what was going on,
and we'd buy it then.
But Greg, you're on because you're
going to be doing it in the future.
Right.
Yeah, well, I think Warren, you said it really well.
I mean, the framework's been laid out.
We know how you approach it and how you and Charlie have
approached it, and really don't see that framework changing.
When the opportunity presents itself,
we'll want to be an active repurchaser of Berkshire shares.
We think it's a great outcome for Berkshire Sherholders
to own a larger piece of each of our operating businesses
and the portfolio, the equity companies,
when the opportunity presents itself.
- It can be the dumbest thing you can do,
or it can be the smartest thing you can do.
And to make it more complicated than that
and start getting into all this,
but you obviously do what the business needs to do first,
that the opportunities are there, grow your present business,
buy additional business, whatever it may be.
And then you make a decision on dividends,
but that decision becomes pretty irrevocable
because you don't cut dividends
without having major effects in your shareholder base
and a lot of things.
And then if you got ample capital
and you don't see that you're going to use it all
and your stock is attractive and enhances the intrinsic value
for the remaining shareholders, it's an old brainer.
And if it's above the price of intrinsic value,
it's a no brainer that you don't even listen to anybody,
no matter what investment banker comes in
and tells you here's how to do a repurchase program.
Okay, station one.
- I'm Tom Nelson, a podcast here
from North Oaks, Minnesota.
Charlie, in 2022, you used phrases like,
really massively stupid, massive kind of ignorance,
and crazy to describe what you said
was the 30% of Americans hesitant to submit themselves
to untested mRNA COVID gene therapy.
Do you stand behind those quotes today?
- Yeah, sure.
[APPLAUSE]
Well, we got time for one more than before lunch.
[LAUGHTER]
Becky?
OK.
[LAUGHTER]
I was out, but let's see.
[APPLAUSE]
How about--
[INAUDIBLE]
--see here.
It's going to be how about lunch pretty soon.
I know.
OK.
I've got one for you.
This one comes from Drew Estes.
This is a question for Warren.
In your 1969 letter to partners, you said, "In any company where the founder and chief
driving force behind the enterprise is still active, it's still very difficult to evaluate
second men.
The only real way to see how someone is going to do when running a company is to let them
run it."
This wise statement now applies to Berkshire.
the second man are running Berkshire, what would you advise owners of Berkshire to watch
for, specifically what actions, if taken, should give us concern?
Well, I think I would have some comfort in the fact that 99% of my net worth is in that
company.
So I probably got a stronger interest in it, and perhaps 100 billion or more of philanthropy
will be affected by it.
But I would say that I don't have a second choice.
I mean, it is that tough to find, but I've also seen Greg in action.
I feel 100% comfortable and like they say, I don't know.
Something happened to Greg.
I would tell the directors, you know, they have a problem and they won't.
I don't have anybody to name and if they put somebody in, Berkshire on automatic pilot
can work extremely well for a long time.
I mean, it doesn't like the businesses go away or anything, sort.
And you can't.
It's hard to judge successor management in a really good business because if they don't
show up at the office it'll keep working for a long time.
And maybe that useful input may show itself in five years.
It may go a long, long, long time.
And how are the shareholders advised by a bunch of people that are concerned about whether
you're meeting earnings projections or something, telling them whether the management's any
good thing. You know, it is very, very hard. It's very hard. I've been on the board of
20 companies. It's very hard. If you ask me to rank the management of each one, it's very
difficult to do because some are just better businesses than others. Some would be better
off not managed hardly at all. Others really need help, but they got a lousy business.
And Tom Murphy told me a long, long, long time ago, he said the secret of business is
to buy a good business.
And it's okay to inherit one too.
And Greg is inheriting a good business and I think it will make it better.
But I don't think it's easy to put any one of the next ten nominees in and try and judge
three years later whether they've done a good job or not.
So it's going to be a, that'll be a very interesting job for the board.
and they shouldn't listen to Wall Street on it.
They've got the job.
If they put somebody in, there's a surprise.
We both go down on a plane, they put somebody in.
They've got a real job in assessing that person.
It'll depend on how good he or she is as a talker.
It'll depend on them courting Wall Street
to be supportive of all kinds of things.
And we've got some very good people on the board,
but they would be challenged in that position
as would I where I've been in that position
in other companies where a very great leader has left.
And on the way back from the funeral,
you know, nobody knows what to do exactly.
So with that cheery message, we will go to lunch
and we will come back.
(audience applauding)
We'll see you at one o'clock.
Thank you, Owen.
And we're still gonna try and get 60 questions in.
We've done 25 so far.
Yeah, 25.
So keep the question short
and I'll try and keep the answer short.
Thanks.
[BLANK_AUDIO]