this program is brought to you by Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
it now gives me great pleasure to introduce this year's commencement
speaker Steve Jobs
the chief executive officer and co-founder of Apple and Pixar Animation
Studios Stanford University has been characterized since its founding by a
willingness to be bold and to strike out in new directions and this is a
characteristic very much shared by today's speaker a pioneer and visionary
for almost three decades his name and the companies he has founded have been
synonymous with innovation and creativity as a young boy growing up in
Los Altos Steve Jobs came of age at the same time as Silicon Valley while still
in school he attended lectures informally at
Stanford as well as at youlet Packard where he spent a summer working after
graduating from high school he left California to attend Reed College a trek
through India and a short stint as a video game designer for Atari followed
soon after his return to the valley in 1974 he became a regular along with
Steve Wozniak at meetings of the homebrew Computer Club held at the
Stanford Linear Accelerator Center it was not long before the two of them had
built the prototype for the Apple one the Apple one was very fast at the time
reading and writing for kilobytes in about 20 seconds
about 20,000 times slower than we do so today the Apple 2 was faster still but
more importantly introduced color monitors into the home market in the
mid-1980s the Macintosh became the first truly user-friendly personal computer
you didn't have to be an expert to set it up or to load software or to transfer
information between applications and the mouse offered point-and-click
convenience and opened the door to computer literacy for everyone I still
remember the amazed faces of onlookers as they saw a computer that was
completely different from the personal computers of that day Steve also
co-founded Pixar Animation Studios which has revolutionized the film industry in
its short history with brilliant use of technology and produced two Academy
award-winning films Toy Story and Finding Nemo
since has returned to Apple eight years ago Steve has reinvented the company
once again extending its vision to music and new digital media iPod and iTunes
have changed the way we listen to organize store and purchase our music
and in my case the way I often read books now songs we love are just 99
cents and a completely legal click away
iPhoto and iMovie revolutionized the ability of consumers to organize edit
and display digital photography and video putting capabilities that once
cost thousands of dollars into the hands of every Mac user Steve is also widely
recognized for his ability to create an innovative environment inside Apple as
well as an external company image that is equally innovative just think about
Apple's marketing campaigns over the past three decades a promotional flyer
in 1976 showed Isaac Newton sitting under a tree just as an apple was
falling by with the catchy exhortation to bite B yte into an apple there was an
iconic Superbowl commercial techy humor an iconic Superbowl commercial telling
us that the Macintosh was on the horizon and assuring us that we would see why
1984 wouldn't be like 1984 and in the late 1990s we saw banners and billboards
featuring Pablo Picasso Albert Einstein Martha Graham and Mahatma Gandhi all
urging us to think different Steve Jobs understands the creativity and
innovation start by thinking differently he has a deep-rooted belief in the power
of Education to transform lives coupled with the desire to make the
world a better place from the earliest days of Apple he worked to develop
partnerships with educators and get computers into schools for almost three
decades he and his companies have provided invaluable technology and
supports to schools and communities increasing accessibility to information
for learners of all ages more than 100 years ago in describing his vision for a
new University leland stanford rode the imagination needs to be cultivated and
developed to assure success in life stanford clearly understood that
technical knowledge was only the starting point for creation and
discovery Steve Jobs understands that the computer is a very powerful tool in
a technical sense but that it's true power lies in the ability to unleash the
imagination and creativity of the user as he explained to the New York Times in
a 1997 interview the Macintosh turned out so well because the people working
on it were musicians artists poets and
historians who also happen to be excellent computer scientists and last
fall a Businessweek reporter asked how he manages for innovation his answer was
deceptively simple we hire people who want to make the best things in the
world Steve Jobs personifies the spirit and creativity that have characterized
this university since its founding 114 years ago and we are pleased to have him
here today please join me in warmly welcoming this year's commencement
speaker Steve Jobs
thank you I'm honored to be with you today for your commencement from one of
the finest universities in the world
truth be told I never graduated from college and this is the closest I've
ever gotten to a college graduation
today I want to tell you three stories from my life that's it no big deal just
three stories the first story is about connecting the dots I dropped out of
Reed College after the first six months but then stayed around as a drop in for
another 18 months or so before I really quit so why did I drop out it started
before I was born my biological mother was a young unwed graduate student and
she decided to put me up for adoption she felt very strongly that I should be
adopted by college graduates so everything was all set for me to be
adopted at Birth by a lawyer and his wife except that when I popped out they
decided at the last minute that they really wanted a girl so my parents who
were on a waiting list got a call in the middle of the night asking we've got an
unexpected baby boy he want him they said of course my biological mother
found out later that my mother had never graduated from college and that my
father had never graduated from high school she refused to sign the final
adoption papers she only relented a few months later when my parents promised
that I would go to college this was the start in my life and 17 years later I
did go to college but I naively chose a college that was almost as expensive as
Stanford and all of my working-class parents savings were being spent on my
college tuition after six months I couldn't see the value in it I had no
idea what I wanted to do with my life and no idea how college was going to
help me figure it out and here I was spending all the money my parents had
saved their entire life so I decided to drop out and trust that it would all
work out okay it was pretty scary at the time but looking back it was one of the
best decisions I ever made the minute I dropped out I could stop taking the
required classes that didn't interest me and begin dropping in on the ones that
looked far more interesting it wasn't all romantic I didn't have a dorm room
so I slept on the floor in friends rooms I returned coke bottles for the five
cent deposits to buy food with and I would walk the seven miles across town
every Sunday night to get one good meal a week at the Hari Krishna temple I
loved it and much of what I stumbled into by following my curiosity and
intuition turned out to be priceless later on let me give you one example
Reed College at that time offered perhaps the best calligraphy instruction
in the country throughout the campus every poster every label on every drawer
was beautifully hand calligraphed because I had dropped out and didn't
have to take the normal classes I decided to take a calligraphy class to
learn how to do this I learned about serif and sans-serif typefaces about
varying the amount of space between different letter combinations about what
makes great typography great it was beautiful historical artistically
subtle in a way that science can't capture and I found it fascinating none
of this had even a hope of any practical application in my life but 10 years
later when we were designing the first Macintosh computer it all came back to
me and we designed it all into the Mac it was the first computer with beautiful
typography if I had never dropped in on that single course in college the Mac
would have never had multiple typefaces or proportionally spaced fonts and since
windows just copied the Mac it's likely that no personal computer
if I had never dropped out I would have never dropped in on that calligraphy
class and personal computers might not have the wonderful typography that they
do of course it was impossible to connect the dots looking forward when I
was in college but it was very very clear looking backwards ten years later
again you can't connect the dots looking forward you can only connect them
looking backwards so you have to trust that the dots will somehow connect in
your future you have to trust in something your gut destiny life karma
whatever because believing that the dots will connect down the road will give you
the confidence to follow your heart even when it leads you off the well-worn path
and that will make all the difference my second story is about love and loss I
was lucky I found what I loved to do early in life woz and I started Apple in
my parent's garage when I was 20 we worked hard and in 10 years Apple had
grown from just the two of us in a garage into a two billion dollar company
with over 4,000 employees we just released our finest creation the
Macintosh a year earlier and I just turned 30 and then I got fired how can
you get fired from a company you started well as Apple grew we hired someone who
I thought was very talented to run the company with me and for the first year
or so things went well but then our visions of the future began to diverge
and eventually we had a falling out when we did our Board of Directors sided with
him and so at 30 I was out and very publicly out what had been the focus of
my entire adult life was gone and it was devastating I really didn't know what to
do for a few months I felt that I had let the previous generation of
entrepreneurs down that I had dropped the baton as it was being passed to me I
met with David Packard and Bob Noyce and tried to apologize for screwing up so
badly I was a very public failure and I even
thought about running away from the valley but something slowly began to
dawn on me I still loved what I did the turn of events at Apple had not changed
that one bit I've been rejected but I was still in love and so I decided to
start over I didn't see it then but it turned out that getting fired from Apple
was the best thing that could have ever happened to me the heaviness of being
successful was replaced by the lightness of being a beginner again less sure
about everything it freed me to enter one of the most creative periods of my
life during the next five years I started a company named next another
company named Pixar and fell in love with an amazing woman who would become
my wife Pixar went on to create the world's first computer animated feature
film Toy Story and is now the most successful animation studio in the world
in a remarkable turn of events Apple bought next and I returned to Apple and
the technology we developed it next is at the heart of Apple's current
Renaissance and Laureen and I have a wonderful family together I'm pretty
sure none of this would have happened if I hadn't been fired from Apple
it was awful tasting medicine but I guess the patient needed it sometime
life sometimes life's going to hit you in the head with a brick don't lose
faith I'm convinced that the only thing that kept me going was that I loved what
I did you've got to find what you love and that is as true for work as it is
for your lovers your work is going to fill a large part of your life and the
only way to be truly satisfied is to do what you believe is great work and the
only way to do great work is to love what you do if you haven't found it yet
keep looking and don't settle as with all matters of the heart you'll know
when you find it and like any great relationship it just gets better and
better as the years roll on so keep looking don't settle
my third story is about death when I was 17 I read a quote that went something
like if you live each day as if it was your last someday you'll most certainly
be right it made an impression on me and since then for the past 33 years I've
looked in the mirror every morning and asked myself if today were the last day
of my life what I want to do what I am about to do today and whenever the
answer has been no for too many days in a row I know I need to change something
remembering that I'll be dead soon is the most important tool I've ever
encountered to help me make the big choices in life because almost
everything all external expectations all pride all fear of embarrassment or
failure these things just fall away in the face of death leaving only what is
truly important remembering that you are going to die is the best way I know to
avoid the trap of thinking you have something to lose you are already naked
there is no reason not to follow your heart about a year ago I was diagnosed
with cancer I had a scan at 7:30 in the morning and it clearly showed a tumor on
my pancreas I didn't even know what a pancreas was the doctors told me this
was almost certainly a type of cancer that is incurable and that I should
expect to live no longer than three to six months my doctor advised me to go
home and get my affairs in order which is doctors code for prepare to die it
means to try and tell your kids everything you thought you'd have the
next 10 years to tell them in just a few months it means to make sure everything
is buttoned up so that will be as easy as possible for your family it means to
say your goodbyes I live with that diagnosis all day later that evening I
had a biopsy where they stuck an endoscope down my throat through my
stomach and into my intestines put a needle into my pancreas and got a few
cells from the tumor I was sedated but my wife who was there
told me that when they viewed the cells under a microscope the doctor started
crying because it turned out to be a very rare form of pancreatic cancer that
is curable with surgery I had the surgery and thankfully I'm fine now
this was the closest I've been to facing death and I hope it's the closest I get
for a few more decades having lived through it I can now say this to you
with a bit more certainty than when death was a useful but purely
intellectual concept no one wants to die even people who want to go to heaven
don't want to die to get there and yet death is the destination we all
share no one has ever escaped it and that is as it should be because death is
very likely the single best invention of life its life's change agent it clears
out the old to make way for the new right now the new is you but some day
not too long from now you will gradually become the old and be cleared away sorry
to be so dramatic but it's quite true your time is limited so don't waste it
living someone else's life don't be trapped by Dogma which is living with
the results of other people's thinking don't let the noise of others opinions
drown out your own inner voice and most important have the courage to follow
your heart and intuition they somehow already know what you truly want to
become everything else is secondary
when I was young there was an amazing publication called the Whole Earth
Catalog which was one of the Bible's of my generation it was created by a fellow
named Stuart brand not far from here in Menlo Park and he brought it to life
with his poetic touch this was in the late 60s before personal computers and
desktop publishing so it was all made with typewriters scissors and Polaroid
cameras it was sort of like Google and paperback form 35 years before Google
came along it was idealistic overflowing with neat tools and great notions Stuart
and his team put out several issues of the Whole Earth Catalog and then when it
had run its course they put out a final issue
it was the mid-1970s and I was your age on the back cover of their final issue
was a photograph of an early-morning country road the kind you might find
yourself hitchhiking on if you were so adventurous beneath it were the words
stay hungry stay foolish it was their farewell message as they signed off stay
hungry stay foolish and I have always wished that for myself and now as you
graduate to begin anew I wish that for you stay hungry stay foolish thank you
all very much
you
the preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu